Welcome.
This week we'll be talking about processes
on networks.
What this will entail is understanding how
the underlying structure can effect a
process such as diffusion.
So we'll do a little bit of review this is
pretty much what you did for your, I think
your second homework assignment.
We'll look at diffusion in Erdos-Renyi
random graphs, we'll look at it in scare
pre random graphs.
And something that you haven't done
before.
We'll look at diffusion in small world
networks.
But,
You know, what we've seen so far is simple
diffusion.
That is, anyone who's infected can infect
any one of their neighbors with some
probability.
However, not all diffusion is that simple.
For example, when individuals are looking
to adopt a new product, it may not be
sufficient that they see just one of their
friends has made that purchase.
Perhaps they want to see until several of
their friends have done the same.
It becomes even more complex once there
are so called network effects in these
decisions so for example if you're trying
to decide between two different chat
clients, some of your friends are on one
chat client the others are on another,
which one are you going to choose and it
depends on how many friends are on each
and how.
How good the product is and we can add an
additional wrinkle which is that perhaps
you don't have to choose, perhaps you can
use both chat clients.
However, this comes at an additional cost.
You, you can't remember which friend is on
which network or you have to learn how to
use both of them, etc., and this leads to
rather different product adoption
dynamics.
We'll talk briefly about collective
action.
This is, for example, individuals choosing
whether or not to go out.
And protest.
Each of them might have a given criterion
depending on, you know, I'll go out if at
least three people including myself go.
So if I see that two of my, if I can
coordinate with two of my friends and we
all go out, I will be, I will be happy
protesting but people might have different
criteria.
So, how can you determine whether a
protest is going to occur or not.
We'll also talk about innovation.
Now,
You might have an idea of the lone
innovator, the lone person who works at
their desk and scribbles some formulas and
then comes up with a brilliant idea and
doesn't need to really exchange ideas with
anyone else.
They just patent it and get rich.
However, a lot of innovation actually
happens through networks.
And part of it is that you imitate that
you use things that others have developed
that work.
And then perhaps improve upon them
further.
So, how does the network depology affect
the process of.
Innovation.
And finally we'll look at kind of
collective problem solving where you need
to do something but your correct answer
depends on what others correct answer is.
So let's get to it.
First we'll go back to diffusion in
Erdos-Renyi random graphs.
I'm going to set up the network.
And here the main parameter is the number
of nodes in the network and the average
degree.
And,
What you can do is then, no, adjust the
average degree and set up the network.
You can actually go from average degree of
2.5 to something like five and for now I'm
just going to say the infection rate is
going to be one.
That is, if my neighbor is infected at a
previous time step, they're going to
infect me at the next time step and I'm
going to simply spread the infection.
So, here's step one,
Two, three, four.
We can observe that.
Now I'm going to lower it down to 2.5.
I'm going to setup the network and I'm
going to do the same thing.
One, two, three, four.
Looks different doesn't it.
I can lower and further.
Maybe just average degree, one point one.
Just above the percolation threshold.
And now if I do one, two, three, four.
See what happens.
So.
I think we're ready for our quiz question.
So this is just a recap of what happened.
And the quiz question is: when the density
of the network increases, the diffusion in
the network is.
And your choices are: faster, slower,
unaffected.
So hopefully, what you concluded was that
the denser the network, the faster the
diffusions.
So if the average degree is five in four
time, time steps, you had a lot of the
nodes infected.
And furthermore, if the density of the
network falls to a really low value and
you're just at the percolation threshold
or below.
In fact, the disease or whatever it is may
not spread at all because there's not
enough connectivity.
So even if it had infinite time it would
never break out of the little network
fragment where it was located.
So now, let's consider the effect of
diffusion in networks which occur because
nodes are added over time.
These are growing networks and we're going
to look at two situations, one in which
there's preferential attachment meaning
that new nodes who join the network will
preferentially attach to existing nodes
that have high degree, have.
Our hubs have lots of neighbors.
In the second example, they're going to,
the network's going to be grown
non-preferentially.
That is, the new node is just going to
pick one of the existing nodes at random.
So let's see what that might look like.
So here, I will let's see.
We can first grow it non-preferentially.
Let me just set that up again.
And now I'm going to, I think, again, move
the infection rate to one, just to speed
things along.
And now I'm going to say take, let's see
how many steps.
One, two, three, four, five.
Okay, five steps and I've infected some
portion of the network.
It's not, not too bad.
Now I'm going to grow the network
preferentially, going to click set up.
And now I'm going to take the same number
of steps so I'm going to click spread
once.
One, two, three, four, five.
I've basically managed to infect most of
the network so, going back just to make
sure we know what we're doing, when notes
preferentially attach to high degree notes
the diffusion over the network is faster,
slower or unaffected.
Hopefully you figured out that it's faster
when we have preferential attachment, and
this is the same observation as always,
that is when you have hubs that are
extremely well-connected.
What's going to happen is, they're going
to get rapidly infected, right?
If any one of their many friends has the
infection they will pass it on to them.
And next thing you know, now they can
infect all of the rest of their neighbors
who hadn't been infected before.
So, having that, the having hubs in the
network really accelerate the, the spread
of anything, disease, information,
etcetera, within the network.
As long as you have these simple rules
that is, that with equal probability here
we decided to one, anyone who's infected
will infect their neighbor at you know per
time period.
Next we turn to small world networks.
If you remember from last week, what made
a network a small world was a high degree
of cluster.
And here, accomplished by putting the
nodes along a ring lattice such that each
node is connected to it's four closest
neighbors.
And then adding some shortcuts.
And what these shortcuts are going to do
are make the average shortest path small.
Close to that of a random graph, while
still maintaining a high degree of
clustering.
So let's go to the net logo model for
this.
And I'm going to at first have no recovery
so, in this model a node is susceptible
and then once it's infected it stays
infected.
So some diseases operate like this.
Unfortunately, there's no cure so once,
once you're hosting that disease, you're,
you're a host.
So we're going to set up the network.
And we're going to infect one and we're
going to allow the disease to spread.
And here the, the, the speed is somewhat
determined by this probability of
infection.
So I guess I could, well let's just keep
it right there at 24.. And, now we're
going to allow it to spread and you can
see what's going on.
And, we can then add a little bit of
re-wiring probability.
This might be all we need and we're going
to repeat the process.
So we're going to allow it to spread.
And this, hopefully, will allow you to
answer the quiz question.
Which is, as the probability of re-wiring
increases, the speed with which the
infections spread,
Spreads,
Does it increase, decrease or remain the
same?
So going back to net logo.
So hopefully you saw that the infection
can spread more rapidly but can use the
shortcuts that we gave it by rewiring the
network.
Now let's add this probability of
recovery.
And what this is going to do is, with some
probability an infected node is going go
back to being susceptible which means it
doesn't currently carry the infection.
It can't infect it's neighbors.
But it's ready to be infected again.
So let's have no rewiring and we're going
to set up a network and here's one
infected node and then we're going to try
and see if this will spread so we see the
infection kind of growing slowly and it's
hanging in there.
Oh,
This is actually pretty suspenseful, but
it dies out.
Now, let's try this with a little bit of
rewiring, maybe five%, and see what
happens.
Now naturally sometimes the disease will
die out because the nodes recover before
they can really infect a lot of others so
I might have to reinfect the network a few
times to get what I'm after here so I'm
going to allow it to spread.
This time it died out so I'm going to try
and reinfect.
See what happens.
So you should be seeing qualitatively a
different behavior in the case of the
presence of rewired edges versus the plain
lattice, and I'll let you examine this
more in the assignment.