Even though it may not have seemed that
way, so far we've only considered simple
contagion.
And by simple I mean that if one of my
friends is infected,
That's enough for me to become infected as
well.
Of course there are parameters, the
probability per time period that my friend
infects me, whether they'll recover before
they have a chance to infect me, etcetera.
But the main thing that makes it simple is
that it's just between me and one of my
friends.
And this makes sense for things such as
viruses that are diffusing or even
information that's diffusing.
It's enough for one person to tall me a
piece of information and then I know it.
On the other hand, there're other
processes,
For example, the adoption of certain
behaviors or the, the making of purchases,
where you may want to consider what
multiple of your friends are doing.
So, for example, say I'm an impressionable
teenager in high school and I, I see one
of my friends wearing red pants.
I'm not going to run out and buy red pants
just because one of my friends did.
I want to make sure that several of my
friends are wearing red pants before I'm
really convinced that that's the cool
thing to do, and then I'll go ahead and do
it.
And as you might imagine, this has rather
different dynamics, so let's go back to
that small world topology and see what
that does.
So, here I am in that logo.
I have created a slightly smaller network
so we can better see what's going on.
And what we're going to do, is we're going
to do this complex contagion process on
top of the network, where the rules are
that a node will look around to its
neighbors and it will adopt the behavior,
that is, it'll become yellow if it decides
to buy.
Red pants, and it will do so only if at
least two of its friends have done this
already.
So to begin with we are going to infect
two neighboring nodes, because unless we
do this the, the infection is kind of dead
from the get go, so no one is going to buy
red pants if only one node in the network
has fought red pants, according to these
rules.
And now, we're going to allow this, you
know, red pant crazed spread.
I'm going to reinfect a few times, just so
you can see what's going on.
And I'd like you to pay attention to both
what is the structure like, where the
infection is stopped, and also, is the
infection successfully using the short
range ties, I mean, the long range ties,
So we can, and let this run a little bit
and hopefully this is enough information,
otherwise, you're very welcome to play
with the model yourself.
So, here is our question,
Relative to the simple contagion process,
the complex contagion process, is it
better able to use shortcuts, does it
advance more rapidly through the network,
and does it infect a greater number of
nodes?
Complex contagion, even though it has the
name complex, has.
In this case, it had a very simple rule,
that is, it was a threshold model, and the
threshold was just in terms of the number
of your neighbors that have adopted a
certain behavior.
However, sometimes what you're really
playing is a coordination game, where you
have two different choices and you're
trying to decide between them.
And as I said in the previous segment,
this could be, for example, deciding
between different chat, online chat
clients, and it depends on how many of
your friends are using each of them.
So it's not that two friends are using it,
but, are more friends using one versus the
other. And also importantly how good or
those, those chat clients, so let's switch
the context a bit and say we're still
choosing between two things, and let's
just call them basketball and soccer.
And,
If a friend chooses to play basketball, as
well, so they're making choice A,
I will get payoff A every time, for each
friend. And if my friends choose B then I
will get payoff B.
And, if, you know, I just have one friend
and they choose the opposite of what I
chose then my payoff is zero, right?
I get no enjoyment if I want to play
soccer and I can't play on my own and my
friend only wants to play basketball.
So let's see how this plays out.
This note in the middle is trying to
decide between playing basketball,
Which three of his friends play basketball
or playing soccer.
Two of his friends play soccer,
But that's not the only variable, right.
And so sure, three-fifths of his network
is basketball, and two-fifths of his
network is soccer.
But there's also the question of which one
of these sports he enjoys more?
So how, is he going to do this, this
calculation deciding between the two
sports.
Well, this is the formulation.
He has d neighbors or d friends and a
fraction p of them are going to play
basketball.
This is the three-fifths and one - p, p
fraction of them are going to play soccer.
This is the two-fifths.
And if he chooses to play basketball, his
payoff is the number of his friends who
are playing basketball, which is just p
d  a, which is the payoff he gets per
each friend who plays basketball.
Similarly for soccer, the payoff, if you,
if you are to choose to play soccer, the
payoff would be 1-pd, that's the number
of friends who are playing soccer,  b,
the payoff he gets or the enjoyment he
gets from playing soccer with each of
them.
So, this means that he should choose a if
pda  d  a is greater than or equal to
1db.
p  d  b, this, you know, payoff from
soccer and payoff from basketball, and you
can reformulate this so that it's, he will
be playing basketball if the proportion of
his friends playing basketball is greater
than or equal to b, which is the payoff
for soccer / ab.
+ b, kind of the sum of the payoffs for
either choice.
And there are two equilibria in this
problem.
The first is that everyone decides to play
basketball and what an equilibria means is
that no individual, given the current
situation, would want to switch, right?
Because if everyone's playing basketball,
you would get zero payoff from playing
soccer because you, there are no other
soccer players, so it's just not possible.
You get to have zero from each of your
friends because they're all playing
basketball.
Similarly, everyone could decide to play
soccer, in which case no single individual
would choose to play basketball instead.
But what happens in between, right?
You have these equilibria, which is that
everyone's just doing one thing.
But, what if, for some reason, you had two
of the nodes switched,
There could be some external reason.
So, let's see a particular example.
Let's say that, the payoff for playing
basketball with a friend is three, and the
playoff for playing soccer with a friend
is two and we have the, the payoff, that
means that the payoff for nodes who are
both playing basketball is three halves as
large as what they get if they both choose
to play soccer.
So they get like, a 50%, you know, greater
payoff.
And, this also means that nodes will
switch from soccer to basketball, if at
least two-fifths of their friends are, you
know, not using a, or, or, or, are playing
basketball.
So it means you know it can be a minority,
it can be two-fifths of your friends were
playing, so much more appealing than
soccer that you will switch once you pass
that threshold.
So let's see how this cascade might occur.
Suppose you have some devious company that
comes and says we'll give you free shoes.
You know, named branded with some
basketball player's name if you play
basketball and you don't play soccer.
And so, these two nodes then start playing
basketball.
Now, this node is looking and it's finding
that half of its friends, so two out of
four, are playing basketball,
And since the threshold for switching over
is two-fifths, now this node as well is
playing basketball.
Now the quiz question is, can you figure
out which node or nodes will switch to
playing basketball next?
Is it going to be just A, just B, just C,
Or some combination of these three?
Okay.
Hopefully, you figured out that it was B
who would switch next,
Because it was looking at its four
neighbors, two of whom had switched
versus, at that point, you know,if you, if
you exclude B,
A was looking at three neighbors, only one
of which had switched to basketball.
And so that's, that's 1/3,.
Which is less than, than two-fifths.
So, it wasn't sufficient to flip either A
or C was in a symmetric situation.
But now that B has flipped, both A and C
also find it favorable to switch to
basketball.
And so, what you just saw was a cascade
going through the network,
Even though it just started with two nodes
changing their minds or having their minds
changed for them,
And then everyone goes ahead and switches
to basketball,
Which presumably is good, because it seems
like the payoff for basketball in this,
you know, fake scenario is higher than it
is for soccer.
There's a NetLogo app, which you will be
exploring a little bit more in your
assignment,
That allows you to try different
topologies,
And what you'll be doing is allocating an
initial opinion, but your nodes are going
to be flipping, a biased coin deciding.
Actually, I think it's an unbiased coin.
So, 50/50, whether they are red or they're
blue and then you can update their opinion
according to these rules and these
payoffs, they can try this several times
just to see how the structure plays out as
to what the stable configuration is.
That is nodes, individual node would like
to switch given their current payoffs.
There are of course, implications for
viral marketing.
If you really can influence some subset of
the nodes, whether by paying them off or
giving them a free product samples, which
individuals would you want to pick?
And so using the same,
App, you can kind of take turns, if you
find someone to play this with,
Otherwise, you can kind of play against
yourself if you like.
So you can take turns selecting which
nodes you initially infect, and then you
can see how the,
What the payoff is as far as how many
individuals eventually adopt your,
product,
Whether its red or blue.
So you would select blue and say I want
to,
Well, now it's red's turn,
And red says, well I want to be right
here, and blue might pick here.
Oh, sorry, we did another red.
No matter.
[laugh].
And here is blue and now we can do
successive updates and just see how things
play out.
In this case, poor red did not choose very
wisely.
So, the question is, you know, what is the
stable set of traces and how might you
optimally select your initial set such
that you would maximize your influence
within a number.
So, having seen several of these
demonstrations, let's see if you've built
up enough intuition to answer the
following.
What is the role of communities in complex
contagion?
Do they enable ideas to spread in the
presence of thresholds or do they create
isolated pockets of nodes within the
network that are impervious to outside
ideas?
Or, do they allow different opinions to
take hold in different parts of the
network?
Hopefully, you realized that they actually
do all three.
In the first case, complex contagion means
that you need to observe multiple of your
neighbors doing some action, or that you
are going to decide based on your fraction
of your network that is doing one thing as
opposed to the other.
And for this community structure is very
crucial, because it provides the dense
linking around the ego that is the node,
that allows them to observe similar
behavior among their friends.
Similarly, though, it can create isolated
pockets of nodes who are holding on to one
opinion or one way of doing things,
because they are seeing that where most of
the friends within the community are doing
something one way, and it would just be
too inefficient or too costly to switch to
something that someone is bringing in from
the outside.
So on the one hand, it facilitates
adaption with in the community but, it
makes it hard for new things to come in to
the community in the first place.
It also then consequencely, consequently
allows different opinions to take hold in
different parts of the network.
Because each community may independent,
not independently, but they may, it may
seem as if those they independently can
hold onto their beliefs.
One last wrinkle that I would like to
introduce and this you can read about in
the Easley/Kleinberg Chapter nineteen, is
that of bilingual nodes.
Now, what are you, what are you talking
about? What are
We haven't been talking about languages?
Well, in this case, it might mean if you,
actually, are bi sporty.
[laugh] That is you play basketball and
you play soccer.
Well, that's great, then you can play with
everyone who plays basketball and with
everyone who plays soccer.
However, typically in these situations,
there's some cost.
So, besides the actual cost of maybe
needing a pair of cleats for soccer and a
pair of basketball shoes for basketball,
Perhaps the cost is your time. You simply
have to spend more time playing both
sports, and you may not get as good as,
you know, if you weren't splitting your
time between the two activities.
So in this case being bilingual comes with
a cost.
Similarly, the earlier example of instant
messaging clients.
You know, just having the overhead of
having two messaging clients open or
setting up a single messaging client to
talk with two different services, and
then, you know, having to manage your
identity on two different clients as well
can be a hassle,
Right?
So there's some cost, but, you may very
well be willing to pay that cost because
it means that you can now interact with
more parts of your network.
Even though they may have the making
different decisions,
So let's try this on the line.
So, switching back over to NetLogo.
I'm going to first of all, I'm going to
turn off bilingual,
And I'm going to, well, this, this is what
you might foresee when you do set up line.
But if you just lay out, you'll see that
it's a nice ring lattice in fact.
And we can allocate the opinion at random
and then we can update,
So just observe what's going on.
We allocate again, right?
And so,
Great,
So we have A is the payoff for playing
blue, and in this case the payoff for blue
is higher than the payoff for red.
Now, I'm going to turn on bilingual,
Which means a node can choose to be able
to interact with both the red and blue,
however it will have to be this additional
cost of two.
So, I am going to allocate the opinion and
then I am going to update and you can see
several bilingual nodes cropping up where
they would like to talk to someone who is
red and someone who is blue and now we can
keep updating.
So, let's just do that again,
So we have initially nodes using red and
blue.
Now, we update.
So see if you can answer this quiz
question, which is, what is the presence
of the bilingual node to do?
Does it help the superior solution to
spread throughout the network, or does it
help inferior options to persist in the
network,
Or does it cause everyone in the network
to eventually become bilingual?
What you could have concluded from the
demonstration in that logo, let me maybe
go back to it,
Is that these bilingual nodes are allowing
the inferior solution, that is red, to
persist versus when we didn't have
bilingual nodes everything turned blue
eventually because it was, it simply had
the greater payoff.
So, bilingual nodes are good in that they
bridge, but in the long run, they may keep
the superior solution from really taking
over in the network.
One last type of complex contagion that
we'll talk about and that is collective
action.
So previously we talked about,
In complex contagion that you may wait for
a couple of your friends to wear.
Red pants, and then on subsequent days you
might start wearing red pants as well.
However, in some situations, you may want
to coordinate ahead of time, because that
first person to.
Show up to school in red pants, may very
well not have a very good time, because
people might ridicule them.
On the other hand,
If three of your friends all, you and
three of your friends all decide to show
up to school in red pants.
Well, people can try and ridicule you,
But you have strength and numbers and you
can kind of, hold together, and, and be
just fine.
So, another example of where this can crop
up is in protests.
If you go out and protest on your own,
sure you might feel silly if you're the
only holding up a sign.
But also, if for example, your protesting
in you know, against an oppressive regime,
it may be very well be dangerous,
So there's strength in numbers.
If you're one of many people protesting
then you're you know, it's like slightly
that you got in trouble,
So you may want to coordinate with your
friends.
So just to sum up, you want to coordinate
that you don't end up here being the lone
protester, and that instead you're with
your friends and happily protesting.
So,
In general, though, different people might
have different thresholds.
So, here is a node who would go and
protest only if four people or more in
total would go.
So, he would need three other friends to
say, yes, we're going to go protest and
then he would be happy going and
protesting.
However, he only has two friends which
means that he doesn't even have a chance
of doing a coordination among four.
This node would go if three people in
total would go,
So, he would go if this node and this node
would go.
However, we already know that this node
would not go.
Now, this node, in turn, would go if just
one other person went cuz its threshold is
two,
So it and a friend would happily go.
But now, this one isn't going because this
one isn't going, and so, nobody goes and,
you know, no one goes out and protests.
In this network, on the other hand, you
would get partial turnout.
This node doesn't have a chance.
It wants to coordinate with three other
people, but it only has one friend.
So, yeah, they're not going to go out.
But these three nodes each have this
threshold of three and they're all talking
to each other, and hence, they'll all go
and turnout.
So see if you can answer this question
about the network here.
And we're, what we're looking for is
whether this network is going to mobilize,
whether at least a fraction of the nodes
will protest.