Hi.
So, here I am with Eric Sun of Facebook.
The first question to you, Eric, is how
did you come to do social network analysis
for a living and what does that entail
here?
Okay.
So I've been at Facebook for about four
and one-half years.
I started as an intern on the data science
team.
So over the last four and one-half years,
I've done pretty much everything related
to data here.
I first came here because I was an intern,
I was in grad school in Statistics and I
wanted to come to a.
I swear, I could have my hands on all the
data I could, I could ever want and more.
So, this is what, this is the natural
place to do it and I've been here ever
since.
So in the last four and a half years, I've
done everything related to data from
research and analysis to machine learning
to building front-end products for our
users, using our big data sets.
Hm, cool.
So specifically for this course though,
I'm trying to convince students that
knowing about social networks and doing a
little bit of analysis is useful.
So, which, if any, of, you know, aspects
of social network analysis have you found
useful in your work?
So, for my work, I would say that, so
these yeah,
Building front-end products with, with
data is one of my primary focuses.
And, especially now that we want to,
We have this, we have this graph of on
Facebook that we call the entities graph
which is everything on Facebook except for
the user.
So we're already doing pretty well at
being like the social graph of people in
the world.
But we're not doing so well yet at
modeling everything else.
So, we're talking about the,
The pages and the places people connect to
specifically.
So with this we have to, the best way for
us to scalably clean-up and model this
graph is to use crowd sourcing.
And when we're developing the crowd
sourcing algorithms, it's a huge amount of
social networking analysis to figure out
what kind of tasks to send users what kind
of,
What kind of what, what we can do to use
social signals to improve our agreement
metrics.
For example, like, how many yes votes do
we need to how many yes votes or no votes
do we need to accurately say that
something is a good judgement or not, for
example.
We also use social network analysis to do
a lot of things.
For example, the this paper I'm about to
talk, talk about where for example, using
for search ranking social signals is one
of the big factors in search ranking.
Cool.
So modelling not just the, the large
social network, but the whole world?
Exactly.
Is that using social network analysis?
Exactly, yeah.
So without further ado, let's see if we
can switch into a slideshow mode.
Okay, yeah, we're fine.
Alright.
So now, I will talk about a paper that
Jonathan Chang, another Facebooker, and I
wrote last year on Facebook Places.
So, this is an example of how we use
social network analysis to improve a
specific product on Facebook namely the
Facebook Places service search ranking
and, and crowd sourcing.
So if you're not familiar with it, we have
a lot of location based now on Facebook
similar to Foursquare Gowalla, I guess
doesn't exist anymore, but these services
all allow users to share their location to
their friends.
And there's a lot of factors that affect
where these users check in.
And the idea we had here when working on
this paper, was to see if we can figure
out where people are going to go in the
future.
So, there's a lot of pretty obvious
implications for this.
One is ad targeting.
We can, if we know where you're gonna go
in the future, maybe we can send you a
coupon, or, or, or, or do something else
that will improve your user experience.
If we suspect where we if we can suspect
where you're going to go in the future, we
can also use that to improve search
ranking in your check-in flow.
Because maybe you can just press check-in
and then the place where we think you're
about to go, will just show up on the top.
Right.
So, in order to do this prediction we use
social network analysis to extract a lot
of features to, to use in machine
learning.
So, for example, we use previous check-ins
that you have.
We also use all the previous check-ins
that your friends have, have done
recently.
And as a preliminary data analysis, we
used an algorithm called LDA,
Latent Dirichlet Allocation to group
related places.
So here, we consider its basically topic
modeling, where you treat the users as
terms and the, the words in the places as,
as the, as words is in the, in the
document.
And if you run this algorithm then we
quickly see that related places pop up
very quickly.
So here, we, we tied running this
algorithm in San Francisco and when we ran
this, some of the topics are popped up
where with these topics, topic one, two
and three where topic one looks like all
our places within the Castro district of
San Francisco.
Topic two looks like I think this place is
in the Marina, in San Francisco.
And topic three are places that are not
really in any specific geographical area.
But rather, they're, these are all, like,
Asian themed places within San Francisco.
So these are people who check-in to any of
these places are highly likely to check
into other places in, in this group.
So, it, it's pretty interesting to see
what kind of data pops up just from using
a little bit of social network analysis,
and some unsupervised learning.
So just to show some more pretty pictures.
so we some of the other [unknown] features
we use around predicting check-ins was
first demographics.
So here, in this heat map lighter areas
mean more check-in activity.
So, if you're familiar with San Francisco,
this is a, a map of, of the various
neighborhoods of San Francisco.
And we see that males typically check into
the Castro District,
Which is a very gay heavy area of San
Francisco.
Whereas, the females tend to check in, in,
in the financial district in, in do you
know what that neighborhood is?
North Beach I think, where, where a lot of
the clubs are.
And therefore it's pretty striking the,
the, how different males and females use
Facebook places.
There's also a temporal feature. So, we
realize that most of the morning check-ins
are around like the financial district
where people are just getting to work and
checking in.
People don't check in as nearly as much in
the morning as at night in, on the right
side of the screen where tons of check-in
activity are to night clubs and areas
where night life is, is really big in San
Francisco.
,, the next step is to actually predict
check-ins.
So we do the standard thing in machine
learning where we hold out some check-ins
and run a regression to try and predict
where someone is going to check-in next
using all these features that I just
mentioned.
And it turns out we can actually do pretty
well.
So, if we want a recall of 60%,, we can
actually predict with 90% precision, the
next place that a given user is going to
check-in which, which was pretty
surprising to us cuz that is,
It's, it means we're doing pretty well
with a large percentage of, of our data.
Not surprisingly, predicting whether
someone will comment on this check-in is a
lot more difficult because that's just a
lot of a lot of noise and a lot of just a
lot more randomness.
So here, we see that with a 60% recall
rate we can only predict with about
six percent precision, so this is, this is
basically just noise, which was not too
surprising.
However, we do see there are patterns.
So we did notice that responses are much
more likely when someone checks in far
from your usual location.
This is typically when I am going on
vacation and I check in to, let's say,
Hawaii, where, whereas normally I live in
San Francisco.
So my friends are much more likely to
comment naturally if I'm on vacation at
Hawaii.
So here at the blue line is, is likes, and
the red line is comments I believe.
And the x axis is the log of log of
distance in kilometers.
So, the, the further away you go, the more
feedback you get on your check-ins.
Not surprisingly, we also get a lot of
boost when someone checks in close to the
commenter/liker.
So if I'm if I live in San Francisco, and
I suddenly go to, let's say, Berkeley.
And I'm now very close to my friend, who
lives at Berkeley,
Then they are also much more likely to, to
comment or like my post.
This is also not very surprising.
And it's good to see this, these kinds of
things born out in the data.
So, whenever we're doing these kinds of
analyses social network analysis, in
particular, or, or otherwise,
It's really important to do enough just
background summary statistics and some
basic plots to make sure you understand
your data.
And to make sure that your data is
standing correct.
And you can figure out if there's any
outliers you need to get rid of or
anything else you need to clean up before
diving into anything deeper.
Alright.
So, just to talk about some of these
applications.
So we, we have this graph.
And right now, the big focus on our team
is to use crowd sourcing to improve the
graph of places, by adding metadata and
removing places oh, sorry, removing
duplicates.
So these, these are some screenshots of
some, some units we have on our, on our
home page where we, we ask users, like
what kind of places is this cafe in
Seattle?
We also have a flow where users can add
data like categories, name, address, city,
town to any place that is not owned, and
help us fill out our graph.
So, there's a lot of really interesting
work being done in this, in crowd
sourcing, in particular.
Because as I touched on earlier we want to
only accept suggestions that, that are,
that are good.
And how do we figure out what's, what's
actually good is that we do a lot of
analysis to use lots of social features
around demographics,
Around whether you've, you've interacted
with this place.
Whether your friends have interacted with
this place, to try and get a sense of
whether you are likely to provide good
feedback cuz on a Facebook scale, we have
users of all kinds.
We have spammers.
We have we have people who just don't know
what they're doing.
People who are, like, very young.
13-year-old girls generally don't provide
really good crowd sourcing suggestions,
we've found.
But using these social features, we
actually can provide some meaningful lift
and figure out what crowd sourcing how,
how to use social signals to improve our
crowd sourcing.
So some other applications which I touched
on earlier is just better ranking for
Facebook places.
More ad targeting and also recommending
places you might go in the future.
So, these are all areas that we're, we're
actively working on.
Alright. So thanks, Eric.
I think that was a nice broader
introduction to data issues and useful
applications.
So thanks.
Sure.
Thanks.