Okay.
So, so far, we have established two
things.
There is a small world phenomenon in
social and other networks, and there's all
this interesting local structure, which we
can capture in part by measuring
clustering.
And this extends beyond social networks,
right? That you have high clustering and
short outer shores paths.
For example, in, you have this in neural
networks, after collaboration networks,
which are admittedly social semantic
networks of languages, and networks such
as food webs.
The first two tie it together.
How is it possible to have high clustering
and low average shortest path where Watts
and Strogatz.
What they said is let's start with a
regular lattice.
In this lattice, every node is connected
to it's two closest neighbors on either
side, so four neighbors total.
And you can, you can vary this number of
course.
And, we're going to start rewiring, or
just adding random edges.
Eventually, it's going to look like
Erdos-Renyi Random Graph because all of
the edges are going to be random.
But, what they wanted to know is what
happens in the middle.
And, so I mentioned two ways that they can
go about this.
They can rewire the links.
So, for example here, this node used to be
connected to this one in the lattice, but
now it has a random tie to a randomly
chosen other node, or.
You can simply just add edges on top of
the existing lattice, eventually getting
something that looks mostly random, but
it's overlaid on the original lattice, in
the ring.
And you just take care not to do some
things.
For example, rewire to yourself, or, you
know, have multiple edges to the same
node.
So, just a recap, you have this lattice,
each node has four nearest neighbors and
we want to distinguish node that we can
tune what is the network look like when
there's a small probability of linking to
a random node as opposed to just your
neighbors on the lattice and what happens.
So, for small p, you know, it should look
like a regular lattice.
For large p, we know it should look like a
random graph.
So, just to check your understanding,
which one of these is a result of higher
rewiring probability.
So, hopefully, you can see that this one
has had the more rewiring happening or
actually, it looks like that in, in this
algorithm, the edges were just added on
top.
But now, we're interested to what happens
in between?
As we vary p, is it true that you can't
have small shortest paths without also
having low clustering or can you find a
sweet spot?
And indeed, if you vary.
P here.
So, this is one percent of the links
rewired.
Here, you have ten% of the links.
You can see that even by the time you have
one percent rewired, the average shortest
path of the network has pretty much
dropped to far below what it was in the
regular lattice.
On the other hand, the clustering
coefficient is still a pretty much at the
value that it was in the lattice.
So,
You got this in between regime where,
where just a few random links you have
high clustering but low average shortest
path.
And then, of course, as you continue to
add more and more random links, then the
clustering itself, falls and will, and the
average shortest path will continue to be
very low.
It's basically asymptote to what it is for
the random graph.
And you can try this out in.
Net logo.
So, you can set this up.
And then, you can vary the probability
like so and observe what happens to the
clustering coefficient and the average
shortest path.
You can estimate how the clustering
coefficient falls as a function of the
rewiring probability p, simply by
considering that the chance that.
A rewiring will form a triad by accident
is very slow.
What's, what's going to contribute more to
the clustering coefficient is the
probability that out of this triad, all
three of these edges were preserved which
means that.
You know, each one of them is going to be
rewired with probability one rise to p.
So, the probability that all three of them
are intact is one minus p to the third.
And then, the clustering coefficient for
this given rewired probability is, then,
is just a drop from the original lattice.
Clustering coefficient times one minus p
to the third.
And this is what the function looks like.
Here, it's on linear instead of
logarithmic access, axis.
But there isn't really such an analytical
derivation for average shortest path.
And here, we can just look at a bunch of
different networks and see how their
empirical properties not chopped with what
we expect of a small world network.
So, the, the thing to look at is these are
networks that are widely varying in sizes,
there are quite different film actors,
co-authors of network substrate graph and
E.coli and the CL against neural network.
This is the actual shortest path and this
is the shortest path and the equivalent
random graph and you can see here that
these values are actually quite, quite
close, if not, in some cases, even a bit
lower.
So, it's not the case that because these
networks have more structure that their
average shortest path is any is
significantly longer than it is for an
equivalent Erdos-Renyi Random Graph.
And then, if we look at clustering,
Here is what it would be for the
equivalent random graph.
You can see rather small values and the
actual observed is much, much higher.
So, these are all highly clustered network
that have this small world property.
So, which of the following is a
description matching a small world network
just to make sure we, we understand what
we're talking about here over and over
again.
What is missing though from the
Watts-Strogatz model?
It's, it's neat that it could explain
clustering coexisting with short paths but
there's much in the real world that it
doesn't capture.
For example.
It rewires the links at random and for
most of us, our experience is that we're
not just as likely to know someone across
the globe, no matter what Chris there is
doing at the moment to help us bring us
altogether then someone who maybe is in
the neighboring town, right?
So, maybe it would makes sense for the
links to depend on geography, yes I'm mush
more like to know people living on my
street but I'm also more likely to know
people who live in the same city.
Than I mam to know people in the distance.
And what about hierarchical structure and
groups?
I mean, you can think of geography in a
hierarchical way here a neighborhood is
part of the city that might be part of a
larger urban area that's part of.
A county, etc.
So how is that captured?
And maybe geography is not the only the
only kind of nested structure that we're
in and we're part of different
organizations as well.
How are those nested?
And then, it doesn't capture the presence
of hubs which we know to play a very
important role in many networks with the
Watts-Strogatz model.
For the, for the original lattice, each
node has exactly the same degree.
So, naturally, there are no hubs but even
as you rewire the model that you're
tending to is that Erdos-Renyi random
graph which again, does not have hubs.
So, the model doesn't really capture a lot
of the real structure but it goes a long
way towards explaining what we do see.
Here is a hint as to how geographic ties
may be distributed.
This is from the original paper by
Milgram.
He says, the geographic movement of the
message from Nebraska to Massachusetts is
striking.
There's a progressive closing in on the
target areas, each new person is added to
the chain.
So, it seems like the way that the message
is traveling is that it makes large hops
initially.
And then, as it gets closer, it's really
homing in using.
Short nearby ties.
So, how is that possible?
Well, John Kleinberg proposed a model of
small worlds that they are laid out on the
lattice so, for example, on the 2D
lattice, he said, in addition to these
local lattice edges, you're going to have
the probability of a link between same
nodes, u and b, to be proportional to the
distance between u and b to this exponent
minus r.
And the question is, what happens as this
exponent varies.
So, I'm going to just show you briefly a
net logo download that I'm going to try
and figure into your assignment.
So here, we can vary what r is and.
You can set up the network, it's, it's
rather slow because you need a large
lattice in order to see how the search
starts to work and then, we're going to
repeatedly be selecting a target and a
starting point and seeing using a gritty
search at each point, each node selects.
One of it's neighbors who's closest to the
target, how quickly does the message reach
the target and you can also bury the.
This probability so we can make the links
highly localized by increasing r.
So, let's just look at what that looks
like.
Hopefully we'll, you should, you should,
you should be able to see the edges, okay,
right, so and all the edges are local and
if they do come out, they're just kind of
being very, very short bridges and so if
we.
Then do a search, you can see it going
very, very gradually because it basically
has to make all these little stuffs.
On the other hand, if we change it so that
we allow many long range times, let's see
what that looks like.
The, the edges might be so far rate to be
being that though obscure the lattice
structure altogether indeed.
And now, we can.
Start and here, the lattice really isn't
large enough to, to, to show what's going
on but typically, you see a very large
initial job and then kind of going along
the lattice.
And what's that showing you is that maybe
it's bested by back to the slides, okay.
So, what you should be seeing is when the
edges are random, you have these long hops
initially but then, there are no short
range ties, you basically have to go
right, to get to the target.
And, you know, there are many other edges
present but none of them really took you
in the right direction.
Oh, sorry, I guess I'm still running Net
Logo because it's been very loud.
[laugh] Okay, so, hopefully, it's going to
quite down On the other hand, if we have
this very high value of r, then what
happens is that we just don't have that
many long ranged ties.
So, again, what kind of ties, you know,
there, there are ties that are heading in
the right direction but we're still stuck
making very slow progress.
And then, finally, ideally, for one over
distance squared, what we have is both the
presence of some long range ties and then,
some shorter range ties once we're close
to the target that we can use.
And this is this concept of navigability
that is thus, the placement of the edges
allow you to, at each step.
Makes some amount of progress towards your
goal and what Kleinberg proved was that
indeed, if the exponent bar is two, that
is the probability of linking to someone
falls one over the distance squared, then
you can make enough progress on, at each
step such that the number of steps that
you have to take only draws
logarithmically.
So, your quiz question, just to test
whether you understood this, what is true
about the network or the probability of a
tie balls off as distance to the -two.
And just to remind you, I mean, I've
brought this up before that the
interesting structure that we see in
social networks, in other networks could
really be a projection of a bio part type
network.
For example, if you have different context
and individuals and then, you have
individuals who share a context have
joined ties.
So, why not model this explicitly?
So.
Kleinberg also proposed a hierarchical
network model where you have these nested
groups and the probability that two
individuals share an edge is proportional
to a constant to the minus alpha and then,
the distance that you have to go up in the
hierarchy to get from one to the other.
Also, if you just or have these nested
groups and then, you have q being decided
the smallest group that these nodes of
interest b and w belong to, then, the
probability of an edge existing between b
and w is going to be q to the minus alpha.
So, two different ways of representing
nested group structure.
Such that you can now not only use it to
represent geography, as I said,
neighborhood parts of the cities, parts of
the counties but also other things such as
individuals who are taking the same class
at a university, who are, who have the
same major or in the same school within
the university, who are part of the same
university, who are part of the
universities in that country, etc.
And at, concurrently, Watts, Dodds and,
and Newman proposed another hierarchical
moment which is very similar that said
that the probability that i and j know
each other is again, proportional to
either the minus alpha x squared, x is
equivalent to h in the previous slide.
It's the, it's the number of steps up in
the hierarchy have to go in order to join
two individuals.
And what was different about their work
was that they looked at navigation when
you have different, different hierarchy.
So, you can concurrently have hierarchy
for geography, a hierarchy for occupation
and when individuals are searching, they
can switch between hierarchy.
So, if I know that my target lives in
Massachusetts but I also know that he is a
sock broker, well then, I can decide oh, I
knew someone who is not in Massachusetts
but is a stock broker or I can choose,
Oh, I know someone who lives in the
neighboring town even through they are not
in the banking industry I, I will forward
the message for them.
And these.
These theoretical models then correspond
closely to what was found in early
experiments, there's a need to reverse
small world experiment that [inaudible]
that there are the same ones who looked at
the accuracy of the chains that
individuals are able to create.
So, they gave the individuals a whole slew
of hypothetical target.
So, they weren't actually running the
chains, they were just curious who would
you pick and why.
And they found that overwhelmingly, people
chose based on geography.
The in-occupation.
So, those two hierarchies make a lot of
sense and only seven% were chosen because
they we're hops, because that's someone
who knows a lot of other people.
And also, there was an absence of second
degree strategies so.
I'm going to pick my friend because I know
they know someone in Massachusetts.
So, that seems to be relatively aware.
If we go back to the e-mail experiment
that was front out of Columbia one
additional nice analysis that they did was
to look at successful chains versus ones
that didn't quite make it.
And what they found with this successful
chain was that they disproportionately
used weak ties, professional ties, ties
originating at work or collage or those
that focus on, on the target's work.
And they disproportionately avoided using
hops and there was no evidence of funnels.
So, in the original Milgram experiment.
It seemed like the last people in the
chain tended to be the same.
To, you know, another stock broker and
maybe a tailor from the from the town
where the stock broker lived.
But there was no evidence of fondling in
this new experiment.
And also people in successful teams used
family and friendship ties less and this
tend to, tend to be getting strong ties.
And the strategy interestingly parallel to
that of the Milgram experiment which is
that individuals first focus on geography
you know like get it to the right country
then worry about what the, what the
person's profession is but to those the
last few hops tended to reach the targets
professionally as supposed to just trying
to narrow down geographically.