Okay.
So here I am, still at LinkedIn and this
is Matthew Bastien who is the creator of
Geffey So the first question, is why did
you do it?
It's, it's, it's an interesting story
about my professor in 2007.
We had these large web graphs.
And there was really no tool to visualize
such large graphs.
So we just decided to create our own tool.
That's the story.
And then we had we had the, the Google of
seminar of code that brought a lot of
students, and passionate computer science
students.
To the project.
And that's, that's how I really started
then And became like a open source
community.
Yeah.
Yeah, so, so seems like it really is a,
community in that people who use Geffey
both kind of report back what their
results are; but they also create plugins
and, and other things.
So what are the kind of the need either
examples of applications or plugins that
you think were especially like you, you
didn't anticipate?
Yes, I mean, plugins is one of our core
mission.
We try to have a tool that is extensible.
And that you know, like networks are
really everywhere.
You can have networks of software, code,
and networks of e-mails and social
networks.
So at the beginning we really knew that
there would be tons of other applications
for not just the core of network graphs
And so we knew that people would like to
extend Geffey for their particular
applications and, and data.
So that's why we created this modular
architecture.
And it really is interesting to, to see
people creating like, plug-ins to get
Like, networks, multi-modal networks or,
streaming.
So we had this great graph streaming plug
in that was created.
And you can basically see Geffe, having
data streamed live to it.
Mm hm.
And also streamed out of it.
So it became more like a platform to, to
monitor networks.
And that, that was really a breakthrough.
And there was this great example of the
Egyptian Revolution that Andre Panisson
recorded live when all the tweets were
coming in.
Hm.
And he saw this natural, construct on real
time.
That was really a breakthrough for, for
the [inaudible] and the community.
Okay.
We'll have to get a pointer to that to, to
share to students.
So I guess if it's not asking too much how
did you come to be at Linkedin and, and
how has social network analysis and, and
can perhaps Geffey in particular served
you in whatever you might be doing here.
[laugh].
Mm-hm.
Yes so I'm a data scientist here and we,
we looked at graphs a lot and.
But that, that's not the main reason why
I'm here.
I think.
One of the main reason is that, when you
work on, on, on graphs and practically in
Geffey you have a lot of interesting
challenges for a computer scientist.
And how do you store and retrieve you
know, large graph structure?
Or how do you visualize millions of
elements on a, on a screen?
How do you create an application that can
be executed in all the platforms?
You learn a lot by doing this.
So I learned a lot on well just by, by
coding basically and that's how I became
like more an expert in this area, and, and
that, that's how they got me.
Mm hm.
[laugh].
So if, if there is any, like, computer,
computer science students who is
interested in, in having some interesting
coding challenges.
We are, having a Google seminar of code
every year now.
And we are inviting students to, to
participate and just show their skills and
participate to the community.
Cool.
So we'll get a pointer to that as well,
and share it with the students.
So thanks for taking the time.
Thank you very much.