In this final portion, we'll see where the
small world structure might arise from.
Now, you can, of course, just assign
properties to nodes.
Such a spatial location or group
membership.
And then, add edges accordingly.
So you can have many edges between people
who are in the same small group.
But people who are tied only very loosely
through a large group are much less likely
to, have an edge.
However, it would be even neater if we
knew you know, something underneath that's
a driving.
That edge formation that doesn't dictate
okay if you're in this size.
Group, your probability of linking is x.
Can we sort of derive Small World networks
from some sort of basic criteria that we
would like to optimize in the network.
So, I'm going to show you two very related
geographical models where we're going to
place nodes on 2-d surface.
So they're going to have a location.
But we're going to determine who is going
to link to whom based on various criteria.
So one such function we may want to
optimize is, you know you can determine
energy or anything like that.
We're going to have a penalty essentially
for The average shortest path.
So we want nodes to be a few hops away
from each other.
So we want to minimize the average
shortest path.
And at the same time.
They also want to minimize the length of
the edges, the actual physical length of
the edges.
You can imagine that, you have spools of
wire and the wire is copper and it costs
something, right.
So, you want to not have wire all over the
place, you want to do things efficiently.
And, so, the average shortest path is just
going to look at all the distances between
I and j, but in a graph sense, the graph
distance.
And, then this other wiring distance is
actually going to look at the coordinates
and see how, How much wire did you expend
wiring these together.
So here's your quiz question,
Given that this function incorporates two
things, a person's preference for short
distances, and a small number of hops,
let's think about.
Two different networks.
One is a road network where you're
driving, and another is an airplane or
actually air transit network where you're
taking a plane from city to city.
So from the passenger's point of view,
what would you like to optimize in an air.
Transit network as opposed to a road
network.
Okay, so hopefully for the air transit
network, you want to minimize the number
of hops.
Because, landing, and then you know,
switching planes, is a very risky
business.
Right, 'cuz your plane might be late, you
might miss your connections, etcetera.
Versus covering long distances physically
is relatively easy in a plane so you might
go from Sanfrancisco to Atlanta only to
end up in Detroit and that's not so bad
but if you're making such a big detour
driving you, you'd be pretty unhappy if
the road network looked like the airline
transportation network.
So let's look at what these networks How
they're structured if you optimize.
And the method here,
And I'll provide hopefully a net logo app
that you can use to simulate this
yourself.
But, what, what it's called, simulating
annealing.
Simulated annealing.
So first, you raise up the temperature
meaning you're willing to accept
configurations that are high energy.
That is maybe you have high wiring cost or
lots of hops, or something like that.
And then you tune the energy down and,
actually the temperature down.
And.
And you get into lower and lower energy
configurations until you hopefully find
some sort of optimum.
So here we have The, the cost of the wire
becoming cheaper and cheaper, and you can
see as this happens, you get more and more
edges that cover more and more distance
until finally you get, you know, kind of a
hub configuration where every other node
is connected to one node, meaning that it
has, you know, a, a very short number of
hops.
Right?
If, if they're all connected to the same
node, and most it's two hops to anywhere
else in the network.
But, you've just exp-, spent a lot of
wire, or you may get configurations with,
actually multiple, hubs as well.
So I'll let you play with that for the
assignment and see if you can, get this
nice, hub structure.
And another cute way of looking at this is
to.
You don't want to do this while you're
optimizing.
Because, of course, then it's going to
mess things up.
Because your nodes now have moved.
And so the distance between them is no
longer accurate.
But you can start out with the original
lattice laid out.
And then, kind of let it, let the springs
do their job.
And so this one has a few short range
short cuts and you can see the network
kind of coming in.
And then here is that network with the big
hub and several, and several hubs.
And here I guess it's several hubs as
well.
So you can actually see the network kind
of contracting due to these rewirings.
It's making it from a large world to a
relatively small world.
Here is a second model with a similar
idea.
That, again, you have some penalty for the
actual Euclidean distance that you have to
traverse.
And then also the number of hops.
And here, instead of starting with all the
links from, in the beginning.
You are going to, just apply this rule
that you're going to add edges.
And you're going, one by one, and you're
going to add the one with the smallest
weight, that is this distance.
So for example if you're laying rail
tracks, so you know, how much track do you
have to put down.
And then what is the distance to the root
note?
So depending on this parameter beta, then
you're going to get different, different
types of networks.
And, in fact, when you put a high price on
the Euclidean distance, you get something
that looks more like a road network.
When, distance is cheap, you get something
that looks more like those air transit,
networks that are nicely plotted in your,
in-flight magazine.
Quiz question, a network that contains
many hubs with far reaching edges is
indicative of which of these following
criteria that lead to the network being
formed?
Okay.
So to recap, the world is small if you
look at it as a network.
Yet it has lots of interesting local
structure, which we can capture with
clustering.
Also we can do a deep dive, look at motif
analysis.
Watts and Strogats came up with a nice
simple small world model.
Other models though, including.
One created by Watts,
Look at other structures geographical
models, and hierarchical models that say
that it's not just random rewiring, the
probability of an edge existing depends on
the physical distance or the
organizational distance between two nodes.
And finally, the way that we get to this
structure may be a result of some sort of
optimization process.
These networks are going to be used, may
be they are chanced networks, may be they
are a result of how individuals have to
communicate within the company.
And, so that makes actually the structure
extra interesting, because it tells us
about the underlying needs and the
underlying processes.
Next week, what we're going to be doing is
learning about how learning and diffusion
are affected by small-world and other
network topologies.
So, I'll see you then.