For the first application, I'll tell you
about some of my own work on recipe
recommendations, and this is joint work
with my PhD student Edwin Teng and a
collaborator Yu-Ru Lin, who works with
Davis Lazer,, whose name you've
encountered before at Northeastern and at
Harvard. So,
What we were interested in is whether if
one were to construct networks out of
ingredients based on co-occurrence
initially and recipes, later, we also
looked at substitutes whether one could
actually predict which recipe is better,
right?
I had approached this as someone who's not
a very good cook at all.
And, I thought, well, you know, I, I've
solved so many other problems in life
using data. Maybe I can solve my cooking
problem by doing a bit of data analysis
and the cooking problem is basically this.
If you have an expert cook, they can
eyeball a recipe and just sort of tell,
okay,
This is, going to be good or this isn't,
Or they can know that, you know, you can
tweak the recipe and in which ways you can
tweak it,
That would improve without, you know,
harming the basic substance of, of the
food.
And, I just didn't know things like that,
so I said, let's see if we can answer this
question with data.
And so, the data set we gathered were over
40,000 recipes, from the site
allrecipes.com.
And we discovered then a rich additional
data set, which were nearly 2,000,000
reviews of the, the recipes, which then
included text as well.
And what we wanted to know is what, what
patterns emerge out of this aggregated
knowledge and how specifically can
ingredient networks be used to predict
which recipe is good?
So,
Out of all this data we extracted the
cooking methods.
That is, are you going to boil it?
Are you going to grill it?
Are you going to chop it?
The ingredients,
And what ingredients are together in the
original recipe?
And what modifications are suggested in
the reviews?
And then we wanted to finally do a
prediction.
If we have a recipe for grandma's Swedish
meatballs, and we have another one that's
the Amazing Swedish meatball, and they
have most of the same ingredients, but
not, not quite, and maybe the cooking
method's a little bit different, can we
use network analysis to actually predict
which one's going to be better?
So, on the way, we kind of did a little
bit of exploratory data analysis, not
necessarily having to do with networks,
and, for example, we found that cooking
methods differ by region.
So you had the Northeast than the South
more likely to fry their foods,
These, these are regions of the United
States.
Grilling was more popular in the mountain
and West Coast regions, for example.
So we, we kind of had a sense, okay, the,
there's, there's some encoding of real
world phenomena in, in this aggregate data
set.
But what we were more interested in was,
you know, how can we apply network
analysis to this?
So, we were wondering whether there's some
combinations of ingredients that might,
and this is just hypothetical, you know,
maybe bananas and blueberries go along
together, but apples and corn, not as
well.
So, for the complement network, what we
did was we constructed edges using the
pointwise mutual information, which is
just the log of the probability that the
ingredients occurred together divided by a
product of the individual probabilities
that and, a particular ingredient occurs
in a recipe.
And so as you might imagine, the numerator
is higher for ingredients that tend to
occur together more than they occur apart.
And, you already saw this network in your
assignment, and they were basically three
main communities of sweet, savory, and
mixed drinks and depending on how you
threshold, and modularity, and so on, you
can find some additional communities in
there.
And, but we also wanted to know, you know,
what kinds of networks can we extract out
of the, the reviews, and even before that,
are the reviews tweaking, say, the
quantity?
So instead of one two eggs, maybe you want
to put three or maybe just one.
And maybe you want to add orange juice for
some reason, or not, or strawberries, or
who knows?
Right?
There, there are all sorts of things that
can happen when people review recipes, and
this is kind of an interesting thing,
which is that right around a rating of
four out of five, which means the person
likes it you see the most suggested
modifications.
You know, this is good but I would add
this or I would subtract that, or more of
this, or less of that, etc.
And this is less common for those recipes
that get, you know, kind of a perfect five
star rating or one's that people don't
like.
If it's beyond repair, they don't really
bother to suggest these modifications.
And yeah,
So that's the, the main thing and then you
can look for individual ingredients.
You know, how, how many times are they,
increased,
And you'll see things like garlic being,
way, way up, you know,
More garlic good,
But maybe, you know, white sugar, sugar,
butter.
The kinds of things that get, decreased,
more than they get increased, potentially
for, for health reasons.
And in general we can see some additional
patterns, for example, ingredients that
occur in a lot of recipes, meaning they're
pretty essential, are less likely to be
deleted, that is people are less likely to
take them out, and they're less likely to
be added, I mean, probably, they're so
common that if they belonged in the recipe
they would have been included already, and
they're also less likely to be increased.
Now, lets look at specifically the parts
that we are going to build the network out
of and that is we looked for patterns that
said something like I replace the butter
with sour creams.
So replace A with B,
Substitute B for A, B instead of A and we
have these edge weights,
Which was the probability that B is going
to be suggested every time A was mentioned
in as being substituted with something
else in a comment.
And this again is a network that I think
you've worked, or at least I've shown it
to you in lecture before.
So if we take the substitution network
already, just laying it out, we can see
pretty clear communities, and then, we can
apply community finding to actually have a
network of different communities which
then we can look within each community and
find, hey, these are the common
substitutions for milk, these are the
common substitutions for cinnamon and
they, they tend to make sense.
Okay.
So these communities, yes, they make
sense, but this, do these substitutions
actually encode users' preference?
And for this, we constructed another kind
of network, which we called a preference
network.
And that is, if you have two recipes that
overlap in ingredients somewhat, but this
one has one,
Ingredient extra or has a different
ingredient than this other one, so for
example one has ketchup and cheese, and
the other one just has pickle, and one
gets a higher rating than another, you
create these pairwise preferences.
You know ketchup to pickle cheese to
pickle, for example, and you aggregate
this over all the recipe pairs with
sufficient overlap to see whether in
general there's a preference of one
ingredient over another.
And, what you end up seeing is that there
is a correlation between the substitutions
that are suggested in the comments and the
differences in ratings of recipes that
overlapping ingredients.
Except, you know, you would get one recipe
out of another if you just did that
substitution.
And so, we have a very high correlation,
which tells us that these networks encode
user preferences.
So, let's see if we can predict you know,
given two different related dishes that
are somewhat different. Can we predict
which one is going to get the higher
rating?
And so, we're going to use a baseline,
which is just the cooking method.
The preparation time, the number of
servings you get.
We're going to use just the raw ingredient
list, so the thousand most popular
ingredients,
We get like a little prediction
coefficient for each one of those, so may
be having chocolate makes the, makes the
recipe better and actually there is very
little signal in that, just having an
ingredient or not.
The nutrition information and then we are
going to include our ingredient networks
and finally we are going to combine
everything.
So for the prediction task, we gathered a
bunch of pairs of recipes that were
related enough that you could really
compare them,
So you weren't comparing pizza with the
recipe for ice cream.
You're comparing, say, two beef dishes
that, you know, two stir fry beef dishes.
And, we wanted to be able to really tell
this one is better than another one.
And the way that we did this was, we
looked for recipe pairs where the same
people rated both recipes and tended to
prefer one over the other.
So we had a ranking and then, we had you,
you know for, for each pair we saw how
well could we predict.
If we would just guessing it at random, we
would be right 50% of the time, right, cuz
one of the recipes is going to be better.
So we like to know are we going to do even
better than that and we tried various
machine learning techniques.
The, the gradient boosting tree was the
one that worked the best.
And, we saw an improvement over the
baseline, which was about 72% correct to
about 78, 79%.
And especially, the ingredient networks
gave us a lot of predictive power in
figuring out which recipe is better.
You can also delve down into the
individual features to see which ones
contribute more towards the prediction.
And the single individual features
actually have, the first three had to do
with the cooking effort and nutrition, but
pretty soon thereafter you see the
ingredient network features playing a role
as well.
Looking within the network features you
can see that the substitution network
actually counts the most.
This is, you know, I would substitute
applesauce for oil just the raw
co-occurrence and the, and the complement
are also important and,
And, and, in a sense, complementary to the
substitution network.
You can further perform a dimensionality
reduction and find which ingredients are
grouped together under a common feature.
And you see that, for example, this
dimension here then contains splenda,
which is a sugar substitute, olive oil,
applesauce, honey, butter.
So it seems to have the sugars and, in
fact, although, in general, these
dimensions are kind of abstract, but it's
still nice to see which, you know, once
you collapse the network,
Which ingredients end up being placed
together.
So, just to conclude, you can have fun by
creating a network out of something that,
normally, maybe, is not considered a
network.
Right?
Recipes, are just lists of ingredients.
But, you, you get to decide, you know,
what, what brings different ingredient
together?
Is it that, they co-occur in the same
recipe?
Is it that they co-occur more often than
what would be expected?
Is it that, one is recommended as the
substitute for another, often,
And, you can then construct all these
networks.
And then,
And the fun thing to do is actually to see
whether you can predict something about
the world using the information of how
this network is structured and this is
exactly what we did with recipes.
We showed that you can predict which is a
better recipe based on ingredient