This week we'll be discussing cool and
unusual applications of social network
analysis.
This will range from looking at the
connections between diseases and genes to
derive a human disease zone.
We'll be looking at recipes and the
relationship between the ingredients and
those recipes.
One of those will be my own work on
predicting recipe ratings from the network
of ingredients.
But also, we'll be looking at a paper that
looks at the relationship between
ingredients through the flavor compounds
that they share.
And so you'll be getting a new dataset to
play with in the assignment.
Also, you'll be playing with the disease
zone in the assignment.
You'll be looking at the social network of
dolphins, and what centrality means in
such a network whether there's
assortativity.
Another subject will be the product space,
which is this network of products that are
related because countries tend to,
Well, if they export one, they also tend
to, are likely to export the other.
And you're going to see what this means
for economic development.
Now, with the exception of the one recipe
paper where I was one of the co-authors,
and so I have prepared a short lecture on
that paper.
I will actually direct you to others,
That is, to external videos where one of
the authors of the paper is actually
presenting the paper.
So this is how you learn about the disease
loem from Laszlo Barabasi, whom you know
from the Barabasi Albert Preferential
Attachment Model, among other things.
You'll be listening to Cesar Hidalgo talk
about the product space network.
And you'll be listening to Yy Ahn talk
about the flavor network.
Now I think this is a bit better than my
rehashing those papers.
We can really take advantage of the work
being recent and being able to hear from
the authors themselves.
And I hope that the assignment is going to
bring it together for you so that you can
see how easy it is in fact to drive
interesting results, simply by
constructing networks in an intuitive and
clever way, and hopefully it would also
make you think about where you would like
to apply your social network analysis
skills once this class is over.
It hopefully will give you a sense of what
are the possibilities with, you know, in
using the tools that you have learned in
this class.
So I hope you will find this week fun.