For our next short video segment, it's my
pleasure to introduce Cameron Marlow, who
is the head of the data science team at
Facebook.
Hi.
And so the first question to you is how
did you first get into social network
analysis?
I first got into social network analysis
by taking a course with Keith Hampton,
At MIT on social network analysis.
It was an introductory course in 2001.
And it was the, frankly I think the best
course of my life.
I don't know if it was the subject matter,
the teacher or both.
But ever since then I've been interested
in studying social networks.
So That's where I got my start.
Cool.
And so then, you started applying it, but
not immediately at Facebook.
Mm.
So what was the path there?
What was the path?
So, yeah.
So I've always been interested in social
networks.
But, you know, it's difficult to measure,
measure them.
So, you know, one, source of data has
always been the web.
And so, I've always been interested in, in
sort of extracting social networks from,
from different social media and online
communities, so I studied web blogs for my
for my PhD thesis.
And went on to Yahoo research where I
studied communities such as Flickr and
Delicious, but I really like was attracted
to come to Facebook because here the
social norms, the site have produced a, a
network which very closely resembles the
real, sort of the real social network of,
of humans.
So, a lot of the work that we do here, we
can.
We can sort of ex-, extrapolate, you know,
more general phenomena about how human
social networks work.
Okay, so can you extend a little bit on
that, what role does the social network
play at Facebook,
How it operates. so its hard to under,
estimate the importance of social networks
in the way that people at Facebook think.
So,
I would say that I was unique in my
research and the people that I interacted
with when, I was at, you know, at, at
Yahoo Research.
But here, everyone really thinks and
operates on, concepts of social networks.
So just to give an example, You know, the
way that we fundamentally store data here,
and, and access it for, like, all parts of
the, the site are, You know is as a graph.
So, most, most of Facebook's data is,
represented as nodes and edges in, in a
very large, graph of people and, and
objects.
And, and, and, conversations.
So, that, you know, it's sort of part of
everyone's everyday life.
You know, and, and some of the social
network concepts that you deal with, in,
in courses like, a lot has come up you
know, in, in every day work.
So, you know, this idea that the degree
distribution has a very high variance.
And there are some people with, like, lots
and lots of connections.
And like, most people have, you know, some
connections.
You can't really build a service, you
know, or you can't really build a, a
product in Facebook without.
Taking this into to account.
Because some of your users are just going
to have such an enormously different
experience with their 5,000 friends, which
we sometimes call whales here, than the
average user that has 150 or, or 200
friends.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Sure.
I guess that's, that, and stay tuned for
more of these clips.
Yeah.
Thanks Cameron.