Welcome to week two of Social Network
Analysis.
This is the Les Matty version of Network
modeling.
Why do we want to model networks?
Because we want to understand the
underlying dynamics that leads to the
observed structures.
So for example, last week we looked at
several networks.
And observed some interesting
characteristics.
We thought we understood how girls in a
dormitory choose their dining table
partners.
However, knowing particular values that we
measure for one network does not mean that
if we go to another dorm.
We can predict what those values will be
for the other setting.
But if we have an underlying model that
tells us well these are the motivations
for the edge formation in that network.
Then we may very well be able to
generalize and make predictions about
networks we haven't even yet observed.
Well this is all nice.
Assuming that your model is actually a
good representation.
Now, how can you tell that your model is
valid?
Well, what you're going to do is you're
going to generate, either through
simulation.
Which is what we'll be doing with net logo
or you can derive mathematically,
properties of networks that follow the
dynamics and the assumptions that you make
in the model.
And if those values agree, if your
prediction based on the model agrees with
the observed quantities, then your model
is a good one.
However If your model fails to predict
some features, but, then you know that
perhaps there's rooms for improvement.
Maybe there are additional characteristics
that need to be incorporated into the
model.
So, for example, if in the dining table
partner networks that you observe.
You see that some girls have many more
incoming edges than others.
If your model is that partners are chosen
at random, you may or may not be able to
reproduce that observed degree
distribution of some girls having Higher
much higher degree than others.
So in that case you may need to
incorporate additional features in to your
model for example that some girls are
intrinsically more, more desirable as
dining table partners than others are.
Or there may be other mechanisms that can
lead to this discrepancy or dispersion in
the degree distribution and we will talk
about some of those models this week.
First, let's talk about the most essential
Model of networks and this is the
Erds-Renyi random graph.
First let me tell you about Erds and
Renyi.
Erds is very famous mathematician who was
extremely prolific [laugh].
Wrote I think hundreds of papers.
And the way in which he wrote them was he
would travel from one mathematicians
doorstep to the next.
And when he arrive, he would say, my mind
is open, let's work together.
And after writing a paper or two with that
person he would go on to the next.
And, this as you might imagine.
It meant that in the co-authorship network
Erdos had an extremely high degree.
And in fact, if you look at the whole
network, there is, it's, it's a matter of
prestige what your Erdos number is.
Your Edros number is one, if you directly
co-authored with Erdos.
Its two if you co-authored with someone
who then co-authored with Erdos.
Three, etcetera.
Mine, mine incidentally is four, and there
are lots and lots of people who have an
Erdos numb-, number of four.
It's not it's not a, a very prestigious
number at all.
But, by being so productive, actually
Erdos ends up being the center of this
very large network.
Now, one of his favorite collaborators is
Renyi.
Renyi is credited with the quote that
mathematicians are machines who turn
coffee into theorems.
Together they wrote a series of papers on
the properties of the random graph which
in this course, and in general, is called
an Erdos-Renyi random graph.
Now, let's look at What the assumptions of
this model are.
There are very few its just going to be
that the nodes are going to connect at
random.
So any two nodes in the network are
equally likely to connect, the network is
going to be undirected so unlike the
dining table partners where you had one
girl.
Picking another as her favorite but this
not being reciprocated.
Here the edges are undirected and the last
assumption or the last parameter is what
the probability is of any two nodes
connecting.
We'll call this probability P.
So for example, any two individuals might
have a probability of .1 of having an
edge, meaning that 1 out of 10 edges that
could exist in the network, actually do.
Alternatively, what you can do is specify
the total number of edges in the network.
We'll call this M and then allocate those
randomly among all pairs of nodes.
Now what does a Erds-Renyi network look
like?
Here I've taken 20 nodes and I've added
some edges at random.
To connect them, the very definition of an
Erdos-Renyi random graph.
Last week, I said that if you apply a
spring layout algorithm to a network to
reposition the nodes, placing the ones
that share an edge close together.
This can reveal some of the underlying
structure, like hopefully you saw with the
your or my Facebook network.
Right?
You should have seen interesting
communities, however, by definition the
Erds-Renyi random graph doesn't have
interesting structure hidden, because the
connections are random.
So, typically when you look at such
network you're going to see a hairball.
Here it's a small hairball.
Larger networks you see a larger hairball.
But one thing that is clear and elegant is
the degree distribution which you can
derive mathematically.
And I, I show this in greater detail in
the math version of this lecture but
basically.
Each node is going to look at n minus one
other nodes in the network and its going
to flip a biased coin.
With probability p its going to have an
edge to that other node with probability
one minus p it won't.
And we have then the degree distribution
which tells us for every degree what is
the probability.
That a node has this given degree.
And as we increase the probability from 5
to 20%.
We can see the degree distribution
shifting to the right.
That is the higher the probability of
adding an edge, the higher the degree Is
that a node is likely to have.
And this binomial distribution then is
very well approximated by the Poisson, as
long as you have a large-ish network, and
the value of P isn't too, too high.
Now, let's look at a net logo simulation
of the Erdos-Renyi random graph.
As I discussed already, there are just a
few parameters to set.
We have the number of nodes.
Here, I've chosen 200 nodes.
And we can decide whether we want to set
the probability of any 2 nodes being
connected.
Or the average number of edges or number
of neighbors per node.
Here, I'm going to select the probability.
And I used this slider to adjust the
probability, starting out with just a .2
percent probability of any two nodes being
connected in this 200-node graph.
I click the link.
I can do the layout.
And what we see here at average degree 0.3
is that we have many, many isolated nodes.
So, degree 0 is the most common degree.
And a few dyads.
Even one node having three neighbors.
Let's see what happens as we up this
probability.
Maybe to 0.5%.
Now we see that the components are
growing.
We can increase this further maybe to 1%.
And we can observe what happens to the
average degree let's just pick one more
value, maybe 2%.
And we should be seeing a denser and
denser network.
You, you can try and tease this apart a
little bit by adjusting the spring length
and upping the repulsion force.
Just to see a little bit more of the
internal structure however these
Erdos-Renyi random graphs once they're
dense enough, really do look like
hairballs.
What the degree distribution tells us is
how evenly distributed the edges are among
the nodes.
What is the probability that a node has
degree 0, degree 1, degree 2?
And all of those probabilities have to sum
to 1.
And by looking at the shape of that
distribution, we can tell whether nodes
tend to have approximately the same degree
with some random variation.
Or whether perhaps there are some outliers
that have degree much higher than others.
So to test your understanding, if you have
a network of size N, meaning they are N
nodes.
Any one node can have a maximum of N, N
minus 1, or N over 2 edges.
And just assume that this is a simple
graph, meaning that there aren't multiple
edges allowed between the same pair of
nodes.
Now that maximal degree, which is
incidentally N minus 1, is not often
achieved in an Erdos-Renyi model.
If you have some moderate probability of
edges between the nodes here we'll set it
to 20% in a network of 50 nodes.
What you'll see is that there is some
variation in degree but the maximum degree
16 is not that different from the average
degree of 10.
And its nowhere close to 49, the act-, the
actual maximum degree.
Now, of course, we can vary the parameter,
so we can up that probability to be 0.9;
that is, 90% of pairs of individuals are
acquainted in this network.
And now you do have several individuals
having the maximal degree, but that
maximal degree is not that different from
the average.
So in an Erdos-Renyi random graph, the
degrees of the nodes tend to be pretty
similar.
You don't have one node having degree 49,
and we might call that node a hub, and
everyone else having degree 1 or 2.
So to further deepen your understanding
I'd like you to.
Figure out what the approximate average
degree of a graph with 100 nodes is where
the probability of any two nodes sharing
an edge is .04.
And I just want the approximate value is
it one, two, three or four?
And one final quiz for this segment.
Going back to the NetLogo model, I would
like you to pick some probability of two
nodes sharing an edge and you can.
It's your choice, but I'd like you to keep
it constant and then I'd like you to vary
the number of nodes.
Starting with a small network, generating
that network, and then increasing the size
of the network, the number nodes.
While the probability stays constant and
then answering the following question.
Does the average degree stay the same?
Increase or decrease?
What insights did this exploration of the
ErdsRnyi random graphs yield?
Well, we saw some things which we will
delve into further about when the degree
is, the average degree is very low,
observing many disconnected components.
We also saw the absence of hubs.
The ErdsRnyi random graph does not yield
networks where some nodes are very well
connected while most others are not.
And we will explore these kinds of models
that can generate such degree
distributions in other segments this week.