In the previous section, we discussed some
of the ways in which the Erdos-Renyi
random graph model is not a fit to some
real-world networks.
In this section, we'll focus on the
particular feature of the presence of
hubs.
These are extremely well-connected nodes
that happen to occur in many real-world
networks, but cannot be replicated with
the Erdos-Renyi random graph model.
Let's look at some of those real-world
networks.
Here is Sun's Java forum, an online forum
where individuals pose questions and
others will answer them.
We see that there are many individuals
that come in and ask, so blue denotes
primarily asking, and some individuals
will primarily answer, denoted in red.
The size of the node denotes the degree.
So here is a node who primarily helps and
is helping many low degree blue nodes.
There's some exceptions, so here's some
blue nodes that have been helped by many
others.
And this node appears to both be helping
and asking questions of others.
We'll look at the degree distribution to
see how it captures this uneven
participation.
Here, I'm plotting the cumulative degree
distribution, which means that, for
example, if we look at having degree 10,
say you have helped ten others, this is
the red curve.
Then, we can read that there's a chance of
one in approximately a hundred that you
have helped a hundred or more people.
This is what cumulative means.
The, the probability up to here captures
the likelihood that you have this degree,
or any degree that's greater.
Now, we see that some individuals have
helped thousands of others.
If we look at the askers, there's still
quite a skew in the degree, but perhaps
utmost, an individual is helped by dozens
of others.
So, can we come up with such models?
Would be good because this isn't the only
network that has such skew.
So, here is a network of reported sexual
partners.
And typically, men will report having had
more partners than women do.
But in either case, you can see a heavy
skew, with the majority of individuals
reporting having a couple of partners, and
then a few individuals reporting having
many.
When we look at such a power-law
distribution, you'll notice that I used a
log-log scale and that the distributions
look approximately linear on this scale.
The reason why I, I did this is because if
you use a linear scale that is not log,
log, what you find is that you can't
really distinguish, is the probability of
having degree 20.
Is it zero, or is it different from zero?
Similarly here for 50, right?
It doesn't look any different than 20,
which actually looks like, you know, the
value's zero.
But if we replot this on the log-log
scale, what we see is that the probability
of having degree 50 is somewhere above
0.000005.
Now this may seem like a very, very low
probability.
But if you have a network of 100,000
nodes, you'd expect actually on average
five of them to exactly degree 50.
It''s useful to know this because you will
actually observe these high degree nodes
if your degree distribution is power-law.
And if you were to just look on a linear
scale, you would have this L, which would
obscure this relationship.
Typically want to plot your degree
distribution on a log-log scale, if you're
dealing with networks that have hubs in
them.
On the other hand, when we looked at the
Erdos-Renyi random graph, what we saw was
a Poisson distribution, which is this
approximation to the binomial.
And here again, if we look at having
degree 20 or having degree 50, these look
pretty much like zero again.
And if we actually look up the likelihood
that a node has degree 50, it's something
like 10 to the minus 26 or 28 or something
like that.
It is puny.
It is actually a true zero.
So, with an Erdos-Renyi random graph here,
you would never see a node with degree 50
when the average is something more like
10.
And so, these two distributions are
actually quite different.
So, we'll need a different model than the
Erdos-Renyi random graph model if we are
to explain high degree nodes.
This power law distribution, because it's
a straight line on the log-log plot just,
it ends up being a line.
So, if you take the log of the probability
of having degree k, it's going to be equal
to some constant minus alpha.
This is the power law exponent times the
log of the degree.
And if you exponentiate both sides, you
get this relationship that the probability
of the node having degree k is equal to
some constant times k to the minus alpha.
Again, this, this parallel exponent shows
up.
Now let's see if you can answer this.
As the exponent alpha increases the
downward slope of the line on a log-log
plot does it stay the same, does it become
milder, or does it become steeper as alpha
increases?
Now, as I said, we need a new model, the
Erdos-Renyi just isn't going to cut it.
And we're going to need two ingredients.
The first is that, nodes are going to
appear over time.
If you think about social networks, this
could be birth, [laugh] or it could be
someone joining a new workplace or a new
school where they, they approach the
existing network and then form social
ties.
If you are thinking about new
publications, the new paper that is
published is going to be citing previous
papers that are already in the citation
graph.
So, just to illustrate a little bit
further, you have an existing network and
here is a node with no connections and
here is a node with three different
connections.
And now, new node comes in and it has some
fixed number of edges allocated with which
it will attach to the existing graph.
So, does it want to attach to this node
with one edge and to this other node with
another edge?
Well, in the preferential attachment
model, what we will see is that the node
is going to prefer to attach to the
existing node in proportion to the number
of edges it already has.
So, it would be more likely to attach to
three times more likely to attach to this
node, which has three edges versus this
node which has one edge.
Let's look at networks that are grown just
with ingredient one.
So, new nodes will join over time, but
there isn't a preference that they have
for joining to certain nodes.
And not others.
The only restriction is that they have to
link to someone who is already there.
So, for example, each node might come in
with two edges.
What this means is that by time t, you
have t nodes, one joined at each time
step.
It also means that at time t, when that
new node comes in with m edges, each
existing node is expected to increase its
degree by m over t.
That is, it's competing with t other nodes
in the network for m edges.
This also means that, over time, the older
nodes who have been around longer are
going to accumulate more edges just by
having been around.
So, if node i was born before node j, we
would expect on average that the degree of
node i is greater than the degree of node
j because this is a random growth process
that need not always be true, but it
typically is.
So, how could one make the growth model
more realistic for social networks?
Should old nodes die?
Should some nodes be more sociable?
Should friendships vane over time?
Or perhaps, all of the above.
I hope you picked all of the above because
even though mathematically it becomes more
difficult to solve such models they
capture many of the realities of networks.
So, in social networks, individuals tend
to leave one way or another eventually.
In citation networks, older papers may
lose interest over time, or maybe for the
best, once their results become so
ingrained that one doesn't even cite them,
it's just known as a general truth.
Part of our knowledge base.
Maybe some nodes are more sociable.
Why should everyone have the same number
of edges?
Maybe some individuals form more ties
simply because of an intrinsic property.
Friendships might vane over time.
Why do you have to keep all of the edges
you had in different contexts from a long
time ago?
And you can probably think of many other
ways in which you can enrich such models.
Now, let's turn to the second ingredient,
which is that of preferential attachment.
Here, we are going to, when the new node
comes in, it's going to want to connect to
the popular kid and not to the less
popular kid or the loaner.
And this process is also known as
cumulative advantage or rich get richer or
the Matthew effect.
Meaning that if, if you already have a
lot, you're going to get more.
And here, we're talking about edges as
being the wealth.
This model was first introduced by Price,
who was modeling how papers get cited.
And it has been observed for a long time
that some papers are just cited a whole
lot more than others.
And here, rather than having the
probability of attachment directly
proportional to the degree, it's going to
be proportional to the degree plus 1,
which is going to take care of a cold
start problem.
And that is that.
If a node has degree zero, it would mean
that, in proportion, it would never get
cited.
Of course, this sits in the case the
papers, you know, all start with zero
citations.
And then, eventually accumulate them.
This kind of process will give you a power
law exponent alpha of 2 plus 1 over m, and
this tends to be in good agreement with
many of the observed empirical
distributions.
Just to look at this image again, so we
have a new node coming in, it could cite
the paper that hasn't been cited at all,
or it could cite the paper which has lots
of existing citations.
And it's going to prefer to cite to this
one in greater proportion than this one.
How does this actually happen?
Well there could be many underlying
mechanisms, but one of them is copying.
So, if you're reading one paper you might
actually look through its references and
find that it cites another paper.
And so you copy the citations of others.
And because that existing paper you're
reading is more the paper that it's citing
has higher degree by which of the fact
that it's being cited, you're then more
likely to cite it as well.
So, it's a cumulative process.
It may also just be that more highly cited
papers are just more highly visible when
you search in different databases.
It may show you the more highly cited
papers first, which again, would give such
papers and advantage.
The more recent and very widely known
model is the Barabasi-Albert model, which
was first used to model the skewed degree,
degree distribution of the World Wide Web.
And in particular Laszlo Barabasi and Reka
Albert were looking at the Norte Dame
website and noting that some of the web
pages had many more edges than as links
than others.
And they considered an undirected model,
even though in reality the web is directed
graph.
So, the process is going to start with
some initial subgraph.
It could be fully connected clique of a
few nodes who all link to each other, or
maybe it is just a circle.
And each new node is going to, again, come
in with m edges and the probability of
connecting to node i is going to be
proportional to the degree of node i.
That is, it's going to be proportional to
k sub i.
And this is going to result in a power law
with an exponent alpha of 3.
3 is a bit high for it's a bit higher than
most of the observed power law
distributions.
However, one can modify the model in
interesting ways.
For example, giving the nodes different
fitness or some intrinsic attractiveness
such that you might, you might prefer
certain nodes even if their degree
initially is lower, and this will produce
more realistic power law distributions and
exponents that are closer to 2 than they
are to 3.
But, let's see what it looks like with the
pure Barabasi-Albert process.
After awhile, you will see some hubs
emerge.
Here, the nodes are sized in proportion to
their degree.
And we can contrast this with the random
growth.
Even with random growth, we had some nodes
that, typically older nodes who had higher
degree.
But there wasn't as much of a disparity
between the best connected nodes and least
well connected nodes as there is in the
Barabasi-Albert model.
So again, this is the preferential
attachment and random attachment, and both
have the same growth mechanism in that
nodes join one by one over time.
So just to review, we have the properties
of the Barabasi-Albert graph, a power law
exponent of three.
We have that the graph is connected,
because we start out with a connected
graph.
And every subsequent node is going to
attach to an existing node which, itself,
has attached through some chain to some of
the original graph.
We also have that the older here are
richer.
And if you track the average degree of a
node born at time 5, which, versus one
which is born at time 100, that node that
joined later, it's going to have a really
hard time catching up to the node that had
the advantage of being there early.
Now, this is not entirely realistic
either.
If you look, for example at the oldest
websites, some of them are still around
and popular, but many of them never got a
huge following.
And that is because over time, there's
some fitness to the different nodes.
Some websites grow very, very popular, and
others fade in popularity.
And it's not all about how many existing
edges they have.
Next, I'd like you to explore these growth
models yourself.
Let me find the NetLogo model.
What you're going to do is, you're going
to start out with just 2 nodes which share
an edge.
And you have this slider, which is the
probability that a new node which comes in
is going to attach preferentially, and
according to the degree of the existing
nodes.
Or maybe, it's just going to attach at
random.
So, let's first start with the random.
And I'm going to click Go, and this is
going to be a little bit slow so I'm going
to speed it up, maybe stop when we have
about 250 nodes.
So, there you go.
You have the degree distribution both on a
linear scale and on a log-log scale.
And you also have the ability now to
change to preferential attachment.
Going to Setup and say Go, and stop at a
similar number of nodes, 250.
And hopefully, already, visually you can
see that the structure is different.
You can see the hubs here.
You can also see the difference in the
degree distribution.
So going back, we have our next quiz
question, which is relative to the random
growth model.
The degree distribution in the
preferential attachment model.
Does it resemble the power law
distribution less or more?
Hopefully, you got that it actually is
more power law than the random growth
model which tends to have an exponential
cutoff.
And we know that actually this should
match the Barabasi-Albert, model and that
the exponent is 3.
The power law exponent is three.
However, it's difficult to tell that from
the NetLogo graph.
But there are ways of fitting such
distributions and arriving the exponent,
which is something that I'll cover in an
extra advanced segment next week in case
you're interested.
So to summarize, we talked about growth
models because networks aren't born,
they're made.
They evolve.
Nodes are added to the network, edges are
added to the network.
And we saw a couple of properties of these
very basic growth models.
The first is that, because nodes join over
time, if a node is older, it's more likely
to have accumulate edges.
But the true hubs you get when you have
preferential attachment, that is, it isn't
enough for the node to just kind of lie
back and wait for edges to come in.
The new nodes have to prefer a
well-connected node.
So, for example, a new kid joining a
school will want to hang out with the
popular kid as opposed to the loner, or a
new paper will want to cite the well-cited
paper as opposed to some other paper that
hasn't been cited at all, or it might do
so accidentally.
Not accidentally but, you know, it's
reading another paper.
And so, reading through those citations,
it's going to end up copying some of them,
and so citing already well-cited papers.
Okay, in any case, once you have this kind
of preferential attachment, you're going
to have the formation of hubs.
Now, in this week's assignment, I've left
a lot of the fun, you know, out of the
lecture and put it into the assignment.
So, even if you're just following the
lectures without taking the course for
credit and you're not doing the
assignments, really you should do this
assignment because it's going to show you
why modeling is important.
That is, we're going to look at these
different models, and you're going to be
able to tell what the effect of the
different growth mechanisms is on the
ability for an infectious agent to spread.
So, this infectious agent, it could be a
bacterium, it could be information, and
you're going to look at different aspects.
So, the first is going to be the
distribution of component sizes in the
network and how this impacts how far the
virus, for example, can spread.
The second thing you're going to look at
is in growth models.
Whether the growth is random or
preferential, or whether that impacts the
speed with which the infection can spread.
So, I think that's the, that actually kind
of, kind of the other half of what we
should be learning this week, which is not
just that these models can explain the
structure of the networks that we see
around us, but that having these models we
then gain insight into how a different
processes might then occur differently
depending on how the network grew or it
came to be.
So, I hope you will find that fun and I'll
see you next week.