Hello.
Welcome to week two of Social Network
Analysis.
This week we'll be focusing on modeling
social networks.
Now why would you want to model social
networks?
Just last week we showed how you can learn
many interesting things just by analyzing
the network structure of real world
networks.
What good is a model?
Well a model is going to be a simple
representation of that real world complex
network and it's going to allow you to
test certain assumptions because in order
to formulate your model you have implement
those assumptions and see whether the
network that is generated from your model
in any way resembles the real world
network that you're seeing.
So for example if you were looking at a
social network and you discovered that
some people had many more friends than
others.
You could say oh, well I think that.
What's leading to this is just a random
fluctuation.
So people meet and form edges at random
and some people are going to have more
edges and some people are going to have
fewer edges and that's my model.
It's going to be a completely random graph
model.
Well, what happens next is that you can
test this.
You can generate networks according to
your model and see if indeed you get some
individuals who have many more friends
than others.
If this doesn't happen you know if your
model can't reproduce the, the
distribution of degrees that you see in
the real network, well, that means that
your model needs to be adjusted.
That the way you're thinking about the
world and the way that friendship
formation functions is actually not, not
what you thought.
Your model needs to be extended.
These kinds of models also often just
serve as a straw man.
Right?
So you know that the model, it's not, it's
not realistic, right?
People don't just meet at random but you'd
like to know exactly how your network is
different from such a random network, and
that gives you further insight about the
measurements that you're taking on your
real world network.
Because, if your real world network is
looking very similar to the, to say, a
random graph model, you can see, there's
not much interest in going on, here.
But if it looks very different, if the
number Numbers you get from the model
versus the numbers you get in your real
network are very divergent then you can
say uh-huh, this an interesting feature
of, of my real world network, and that is
what I will pursue further.
This very basic network model was first
formulated by Erdos and Renyi.
They're two Hungarian mathematicians,
Erdos was an eccentric.
He was very, very productive.
He traveled from conference to conference,
from one collaborator's door to the next,
saying, my mind is open, let's write some
papers.
And after he would finish the papers he
would move on to the next place.
There's actually a network, of coauthors
that it's prestigious to be close to Erdos
and so if you have an Erdos number of one,
it means you are one of his many, many
direct collaborators.
If you have an Erdos number of two, it
means you are a collaborator of a
collaborator.
So people like to calculate their Erdos
number.
Mine is four by the way, which isn't
impressive at all.
He collaborated a lot with Renyi, who, is
actually credited with the quote,
mathematicians are just machines that, who
turn coffee into theorems.
He and Erdos were very, productive, and
among their 32 publications are several
well known ones on the Erdos and Renyi
random graph model, where they could
exactly derive a lot of results about
precisely this model of a network where
you connect nodes at random.
There basically very few assumptions here
besides the size of the network, the
number of nodes.
You just have the probability that any two
nodes are connected.
This is the probability P.
An alternative formulation is that you
determine the total number of edges, M.
And, the mathematical treatment is a
little bit more difficult in the second
case.
And in any case, the two formulations
become very similar once the network is
large.
So we'll focus on the first one, where
you're just fixing the probability that
any two nodes are connected.
What do these networks look like?
Here, I've laid out the nodes on a circle.
Just, I think it's twenty nodes.
And I've added some edges at random.
As we learned last week, sometimes a
layout is more effective if nodes that are
directly connected are close to each other
in the layout, so I applied a spring
layout algorithm, and got this very
typical shape of, of an Erdos-Renyi random
graph.
The first thing that we can derive for
the, Erdos-Renyi random graph is its
degree distribution.
This tells us how many nodes in the
network have no neighbors?
How many of them have one neighbor?
How many of them have two neighbors,
etcetera?
It's going to get a little bit
mathematical.
But if you've ever had basic probability
and statistics, you recognize the binomial
distribution.
This is all it is.
And, if you've never had, this level of
math, don't worry.
It's not, what I'm going to say, you can
also build just through intuition and
through playing with the demo.
So it's not that you have to derive the
binomial distribution from scratch or
anything like that.
I'm bringing it in more just to show, hey,
if you're a mathematician, there's a whole
lot of interesting things and properties
you can derive about networks.
And actually I, I'm just going to be
scratching the, the surface of that.
So that, that is the, the goal.
To illustrate how you can intuit some
properties when you have a nice model of
the network.
So, again our model is we have N nodes
and, with probability P, we add an edge
between every pair of nodes.
So we're, we're kind of flipping a coin.
Right?
So, one node.
Out of the N, it's going to look at the N
minus one other nodes.
And for each one it's going to flip a coin
to see whether they're going to share an
edge or not.
Now, to test your understanding, I'd like
you to imagine a network.
And you're keeping the probability that
any two nodes are connected.
The value P, you're holding constant.
And you're increasing the size of the
network, the number of nodes.
I want you to think about what happens to
the average degree.
How many other nodes on average, is a node
connected to?
To help you with this, I have created a
net logo model.
So let me just try and get into that
model.
And, what you're going to do is you're
going to make sure that this probability
or not is sent to probability.
You're going to have, you're not going to
use this number of neighbors.
You're going to fix the probability of
linking.
Here, I'm just made it two percent in
order to start with 100 nodes, so I'm just
going to click this Erdos-Renyi button and
maybe I'll let it lay out, just to see
what it looks like.
So let me try that a few more times and
here I see the average degree.
Now I'll increase this to maybe 300 and
generate another Erdos-Renyi random graph.
I'm also going to look at the average
degree.
I might do that a few more times and.
I might increase to almost 1000 nodes.
Again, generating Erdos-Renyi Random
Graph.
Has to work a little bit harder for a
larger graph.
And then I'm going to, again, look at the
average degree.
So see if you can understand what's going
on in, in this case.
Now that we've seen what these random
networks characteristically look like, we
can return to the problem of deriving the
degree distribution.
The degree distribution is just a
probability distribution that's going to
say, the probability that a node has
degree zero.
Meaning no neighbors is a certain
quantity.
The probability that it has a one is this.
The probability that it has two neighbors,
it's something else, etcetera.
So this is our, probability distribution.
And the probabilities, of course, have to
sum to one.
Back to how this might happen if we are
doing a little thought experiment is that,
the each node is looking at the n-1 other
nodes and its flipping a biased coin,
which was probability P is going to say,
link to that particular node and with
probability 1-P is going to say uh-uh, not
that one.
And the distribution that describes this
process exactly, the coin flipping, is the
binomial distribution.
So what we're interested in is out of n-1
tries, what is the probability that k of
them are successful.
That is, what is the probability that the
node will have degree k and first we need
to know the number of different ways that
we can choose k nodes out of n minus one.
This is the binomial coefficient times the
probability that you succeeded k times,
which is p to the k times the probability
that you failed.
N minus one minus k times, which is one
minus p to the n minus one minus k.
So lets do a little bit of comprehension
here.
So, what is the maximum degree that a node
can have in a graph that has n nodes?
And here we're assuming that the graph is
simple, meaning that there, you can't have
multiple edges between two nodes.
It's like two people can only have one
friendship.
They can't have two or three or four
friendships between them.
So, and this is the kind of graph that
Erdos and Renyi model random graph.
So what is the maximum degree in this
case?
Let's delve a little bit more into the
binomial distribution.
For a lot of you, this will be a review of
basic probability, but let's do it
nonetheless.
So imagine that you have an eight node
graph with a probability P of any two
nodes being connected.
What we'd like to know is what is the
probability that any given node is
connected to four others?
And we're going to color those blue, and
the three nodes that it's not connected to
we're going to color white.
First we need the binomial coefficient,
which is going to say what is the number
of ways you can choose four out of seven?
Well, you can imagine first that you can
uniquely identify all the nodes.
So that it matters whether, you know, A
goes first, B goes second, or B goes
first, A goes second.
Right?
And there are.
Seven factorial different ways of making
such an ordering because for the first
spot you have seven traces, for the second
spot you have the remaining six, third
spot you have remaining five etcetera.
So this is seven factorial, if you could
distinguish all of the nodes separately,
but what we are saying is that, we don't.
We only have, we're only distinguishing at
the level of whether a trial was
successful or not.
So whether a node is white or blue.
Which means that the three white nodes are
just completely swappable.
So our seven factorial is now divided by a
three factorial in the denominator which
is the number of different arrangements
that we now don't distinguish between.
Similarly for the nodes that we did
connect to, there are four factorial
different ways of ordering them and now we
don't care about their particular
ordering.
So we have another factor of four
factorial in the denominator.
So in general, this binomial coefficient
of choosing, for example here, k items out
of n-1, is going to be n-1 factorial in
the numerator, k factorial in the
denominator, N minus one minus K factorial
in the denominator as well.
And there should be.
Parenthesis around the n minus one.
Sorry about that.
So let's test our understanding.
What is the number of ways of choosing two
items out of five?
Now let's get back to the distribution.
Imagine that we have a certain way of
choosing the k out of n-1 so here it's
four out of seven.
For example, if it was white, white, blue,
blue, blue, white, blue, what we would
have for the probability of that
particular event is one minus p, times one
minus p, times p, times p, times p, time
one, times one minus p, times p, right?
So p to the fourth, times one minus p to
the third.
And once we don't care about the
particular order of white and blue, we add
the binomial coefficient back in.
So, in the end, the binomial distribution
tells us that the probability of this
particular node having degree four in our
eight node probability p graph is 72 score
P to the fourth, one - p to the third, to
the third.
And, that's it.
That's how it works.
If P is equals to .5, you get, this very
symmetric looking distribution, where it's
most likely that the node will have degree
three or four.
But also, it could end up with low
probability, with no neighbors at all, or
connected to all seven of the other nodes.
If, however, the probability is only a
tenth, then you have a distribution that's
much more skewed.
It's much more likely that a node will be
connected to no others.
And very unlikely that it would have
anything past, degree four.
Once you have this distribution, the well
known property such as the mean, the mean
is going to give us the average degree,
from the binomial distribution we can tell
that this average degree Z is going to be
equal to n - one times P.
And in general if you had an arbitrary
degree distribution, the way that you
could calculate the mean, if you just take
the expected value which is the sum over
all the possible outcomes here, we're
interested in the degree X times the
probability of X occurring.
To test our understanding, let's see what
the average degree would be of a graph
with ten nodes, where the probability of
any two nodes linking is a third.
You can similarly complete the variance
for the binomial distribution to variance,
which is just the standard deviation
squared, would be n minus one times p
times one minus p.
And it's computed in a very similar
fashion so we, we won't have to do this in
any assignments or anything like that, but
in general you have the expected.
A value of X minus the mean squared, which
is the definition of variance, is just
this quantity summed over all possible
values of X times the probability of each
particular value that X can take.
The binomial distribution gets quite
impractical to compute, because the
binomial coefficient having those
factorials in there just can't be computed
for very large numbers.
So you typically use approximations.
So, in the limit of p being small, you can
use the Poisson distribution.
And then the limit of, the graph being
large.
So n is large, you can use the normal
distribution.
And the way that, that the poisson and
normal are going to look, for, for large
graphs is that it's going to be a nicely
symmetric distribution around the, the
mean value k.
Of course, if the probability is very,
very low, then the poisson distribution is
actually is, is not symmetric.
Right?
It might be, very much hitting up against
degree zero and then going from there.
But the main point to take away is that
we're not going to be seeing many nodes
that have say, a degree that's many times
higher than the average degree.
That's something you simply don't see, and
this is because this probability drops off
exponentially here as you get higher and
higher in degree.
So the basic insight that we get out of
this is that there are no hubs.
Hubs in the sense of some nodes that have
extremely high connectivity, extremely
high degree.
You just don't see this.