So far, we've discussed how networks might
grow in ways that differ from the
Erdos-Renyi random graph.
What I'd like to talk about next is how
growth, specifically in networks, can lead
to some of the skewed distributions,
skewed degree distributions that we see in
real-world networks.
Here's an example of one such network.
It's the Java Forum, an online question
and answer forum that my collaborator and
I explored to see if we can automatically
identified experts.
It turns out that identifying the experts
was super simple.
All we had to do was look for people who
had replied to lots of others, and these
indeed ended up being the most expert
users as identified by humans actually
reading their replies.
Here, I've also colored the nodes by
whether they have an edge to another
person because they replied to their
question or because they posted a question
and received a reply.
So, the repliers are colored in red and
the askers are colored in blue.
We can look at the degree distribution and
see that it's highly skewed.
It's more skewed in the case of the
replier because you see that some repliers
have replied to upwards of a thousand
other users but it's rare for an
individual to have received replies from
more than a couple of dozen different
helpers.
In this case, the distribution that I've
plotted is the cumulative degree
distribution.
And this means that we're not looking at
the probability that you had interacted
with exactly k other people, but k or
fewer other.
There people in any case we do see some
deviation from a straight line but over
all especially for the repliers we see a
very high skew.
This isn't the only instance of seeing a
very highly skewed degree distribution.
Another example is the network of ah,human
sexual contacts.
And even though men do tend to report
having had more partners than women do in
both cases, the degree distribution for
both men and women is highly skewed.
And this has interesting implications, for
example, for the spread of sexually
transmitted diseases.
Now, in a little while, like next week,
we'll focus more on identifying the true
power laws from the fakes.
But for now, let's just assume that we're
seeing a true power law distribution.
The way that we're going to recognize it
is that we're going to have a straight
line on a log-log plot.
Now, if we had plotted the same power-law
distribution on a linear scale, we, we
would hardly even see it.
We would see this very sharp drop off,
basically like an L-shape, and we wouldn't
be able to tell whether, you know, a node
had any chance of having degree 40, when
most other nodes have degree 1.
But, if we look at the log-log scale, we
can see that even though it's not very
likely just a fraction of a percent that
someone would have degree 40, it's, it's
not negligible.
And in fact, this is what is called a
heavy tail, that is a probability drops
but it doesn't drop exponentially it
doesn't do this.
Instead, it keeps going decade after
decade, we can contrast this with the
Poisson distribution.
Which if, if you remember, this is a
distribution that describes the degrees in
an Erdos-Renyi random graph.
Here, I've even been generous and I made
the average degree be 10.
And now, we might ask the same question,
what is the probability that someone has
degree 40?
Well, on the linear scale, it looks zero,
like it did for, for the power log
distribution.
But, if we now plot on a log-log scale and
we look around 40, we see that the
probability is actually very small,
something like 10 to the minus 10.
And by the time you're over 50, right?
This is [laugh] 10 to the minus 64 so this
is, this is actually 100.
There's no chance that someone would have
degree 100, no matter how large the
network is, it's an Erdos-Renyi random
graph with an average degree of 10.
So, there's a very stark contrast between
the Poisson distribution of the
Erdos-Renyi and the power law distribution
that we see in many real world networks.
So, let's look at this power law
distribution.
What we saw essentially was a line, a
log-log plot which means that the log of
the probability of having degree k is
equal to some constant minus alpha this is
our power law exponent time the log of the
degree k.
And so, if we exponentiate both sides, we
get the, the probability of having degree
k is equal to another constant times the
degree k to the minus alpha.
So, let's check if we understand what's
going on, as the exponent alpha increases.
So this, we're not talking about minus
alpha, we're talking about the, the
exponent alpha.
The downward slope of the line on a
log-log plot, what does it do?
Does it stay the same, become milder?
So, from your point of view, does it do
this, or does it become steeper, does it
do this?
Given that many real world networks seem
to display power-law degree distributions,
what we'd like to do is come up with a
network model that can produce these
distributions as well.
And for this, we're going to need two
ingredients, the first of which is that
the network grows over time.
So, as time goes on, you have more and
more nodes added to the network and more
and more edges.
There are many networks for which this
seems plausible, for example if you look
at citation networks.
When a new paper is written, it will cite
papers that have come before it.
Although social networks are not power
law, and this is not so much that people
don't want to connect to very popular
people.
But practically speaking, we can't keep up
in a meaningful way with thousands or tens
of thousands of friends.
So even though social networks are not
parallel, you can imagine a similar
dynamic where Individuals join the network
over time, whether through birth [laugh]
or another process that they land in a
given social network.
And then, they're going to start forming
edges to other individuals with, within
that network.
There's going to be a second component,
which is that when you come into the
network, you're going to have some edges
that are allocated.
For example, if you're a new paper, you're
going to have say, 30 or a hundred [laugh]
or who knows how many the citations that
you're going to give to the papers that
have come before you.
So, in the social network context, what
you're deciding between, or I guess, let's
stick to the papers.
In the papers context, what you're
deciding between is citing a paper that no
one else has cited or citing a paper that
lots of other people have cited.
In the social network context, you might
be deciding between connecting to someone
who doesn't have many if any other, if any
other connections or connecting to some
one who is popular and has lots of social
ties.
And if you put forth the person who has
lots of social ties.
In fact, if you prefer him in or her in
proportion to the number of ties that they
have, then this is called preferential
attachment or cumulative advantage.
Let's first look at the first factor,
which is that the network is growing.
So here, I've used net logo to grow a
network where each new node comes in with
two edges that it allocates.
So, you can see that some nodes have more
edges than, than others.
But, it's still relatively evenly
distributed, the edges are between the
nodes.
We can derive some properties of the
degree distribution here.
And in order to do this, we're just going
to look at what's going on.
And what's going is that at each time step
you have one new node coming in with m
edges to allocate, which means that at
time step t you're going to have t nodes.
Now, let's look at a node that's born at
time i, and we'll call its degree k sub i.
We know that k sub i on average is going
to be changing at a rate of m over t.
Why m over t?
Well, at each time set, the new node comes
in and it has m edges to give, but it's
going to allocate them among the t nodes
that are already there, so each individual
node is competing with those t others for
the m edges.
We can then see what happens, you know,
over the lifetime of that node since time
i when it was born, to time t.
How many edges do we ex, expect that it
has?
So we integrate the change in, in its
degree from i to t, and we add the m edges
that it had up front.
And this is just k sub i t is equal to m
plus m log t over i.
From this, we can see that on average
nodes that were born earlier are going to
have more edges than node that are born
later.
They've simply been around longer and have
been accumulating and accumulating these
edges.
What I like you to think about isn't which
way this is realistic or not.
So, if you think about social networks,
what other modifications to the, to the
model might you make in order to make it
more realistic?
Okay.
Back to our very simple model though with
no modifications, we just have nodes
arriving over time.
Now, we want to derive the degree
distribution.
And for this, we're going to be using the
fact that nodes that are born later are
going to have lower degree on average.
So, for example, if you want to know what
is the property that a node has degree a
hundred or less, we are going to figure
out at what time a node with average
degree hundred was born.
We'll call that time tau and then the
fraction of nodes that have lower degree
are just going to be the ones who are born
afterwards.
So, this is t minus tau over t is that
fraction.
And we have the solution for the degree of
a node that was born at time tau from
before.
So, we're just going to solve for tau from
this equation and derive an exponential
distribution for, or, for the degree of,
of the nodes.
So, given that this is an exponential
distribution, what I'd like you to answer
is, what do you expect to this degree
distribution to look like on a log-log
plot?
Is it going to be a curved line or is it
going to be a straight line?
The second ingredient we need is that of
preferential attachment.
That is when the new node comes in,
they're, they're not going to just connect
to any node at random.
They're going to prefer some over others
and in fact, the ones that they are going
to prefer are the ones that already have a
lot of edges.
This kind of process is also known as
accumulative advantage process, a rich get
richer phenomenon, or the Matthew effect.
That is, those nodes who already have a
lot of edges are going to get even more
disproportionately.
In fact, it's going to be proportional to
the number of edges that they already
have.
The first such law proposed for networks
was proposed by Price for citation
networks.
In his model, you have papers coming in,
and each paper is going to site m, other
papers on average.
But instead of just citing any old paper
can find, it's going to cite other papers
in proportion to the number of citations
the paper already receives plus 1.
That plus 1 is a little trick that makes
the model works because a lot of papers
start out with no citations at all.
So, if you were citing in proportion to
number of citations you'd have cold start
problem.
So, this kind of helps the process along.
The process generates a very nice degree
distribution which has a power law
exponents with alpha equal to 2 plus 1
over m.
A lot of the real-world citation networks
do have power law exponents slightly above
2.
So, it's just a, a very nice match and a
very nice description of reality, where a
few papers get lots and lots of citations,
thousands, tens of thousands, but most
papers are relatively neglected.
They get no citations at all or just a
couple.
It, you might think, well, preferential
attachment makes sense for social
networks.
If this little node is coming in and he's
saying, well, who's going to be a good
friend to have?
Well, the person who has no friends.
Well, they can't introduce me to anyone
else.
Maybe they're not such a good friend to
have.
But this person here, oh, they're so
popular, let me connect to them.
Now, how does this translate to papers,
why would you want to cite papers that
already well cited?
Well, you know, for one, they're probably
better but there's also a lot of anecdotal
evidence that it's a little bit of, of the
luck of the draw, alright?
You can have two scientists making pretty
much the same discovery, but one paper
gets a lot of attention and the other one
is, is relatively unknown.
So, how can this happen.
Well, one way in which it happens it's, is
through a copying mechanism.
So, when I'm reading a paper that I think
is rela, relevant to my research, I'm
going to look at the references and the
papers that it cites.
And then, I might copy one of those
references, after I read it, [laugh] of
course, right?
I might copy that into my, my own paper.
And if you think about it, the chance that
I encounter a citation to a paper is
proportional to the number of papers who
cite it.
Now, there could be other mechanisms.
For example, the better cited a paper is,
the more likely it is that the authors are
invited to give talks, which in turn means
that more people find out about the paper
etc.
Attachment mechanism.
Now, what really set off a lot of research
in complex networks was the model proposed
by Barabasi and Albert, which is similar
to the Price model, but not quite.
And what they were aiming to do was to
describe why there is a power law
distribution in the number of n links that
different pages receive.
So, in their model, you have new web pages
arriving over time and they each going to
link with m links on average to web pages
that are already there.
And the probability of linking to an
existing page is going to be proportional
to the number of other pages that already
link to that page.
And so, this probability here.
That a given node is node is going to, a
given new node is going to connect to node
i, i is going to be proport, is going to
be equal to m, which is a number of new
things that it has to add the degree of
node i over the sum of the degrees of all
the other notes.
And this results in a power law exponent
of 3, which is a little bit problematic
because the web degree distributions are
much closer to two and three is a
relatively steep a power law exponent
meaning that you don't get the, the most
popular websites would not be as popular
as you would see in the real world.
So but you can correct for this in various
ways, and Barabasi and Albert did indeed
do this later by introducing different
fitness for different sites meaning that
some sites are just a little bit more
interesting.
And so, they get more links.
But let's see how this model works.
So, if we were to simulate it, we would
start say with a connected component of 3
nodes who all link to each other.
And now, we're going to add new nodes one
by one.
But we want to keep track of the degree of
each node.
And so, for each edge, we're going to
record the end points and enter them into
a flat list.
And then, when a new node comes in, so say
4 comes in, it's going to choose from this
list of 1, 1 2, 2 3, 3.
But now, if it happens to choose 3, now 3
has degree 3, and is represented 3 times.
And, so now, when 5 comes in, it's a
little bit more likely that it's going to
choose 3 as well over 1 or 2 actually over
1 which has degree 1 still.
So, that's the basic mechanism, and I've
implemented it in that logo as well so
you'll get to play with that.
After a while, in that logo what you see
is a network such as this one, where
hopefully when you compare it with the
purely random growth model.
You're seeing bigger hubs emerging
relative to here with the random growth,
you have the older nodes are accumulating
more links.
But not nearly in kind of a skewed
fashion, as is happening in the prefern,
preferential attachment model.
So, we can also examine this analytically,
as Barabasi and Albert did.
So again, we're just looking at how the
degree of a node i changes over time and
we've already specified this.
So, at each time step, there are m new
links going around, and they're going to
be allocated in proportion to the degree
of the node divided by the sum of the
degrees.
And here, it's just t times m edges, and
you have 2 end points for each edge so
it's just t, t times m times 2.
And what we'll see again is that if we
want to figure out what the probability is
that a node has degree, say k prime or
less, what we want to figure out is that
what time point tau was the node with
average-degree k prime born.
And then, we know that everyone born after
that will on average have had lower
degree.
And so, following a similar derivation, we
have this distribution that says, the
probability that a node had degree k is 2m
squared over k to the 3rd.
So, this is your power law exponent of
three.
So, besides this nice power law
distribution, other properties of this
network would, this one actually holds for
the growth model as well is that it's just
a single connected component.
And this is simply due to the mechanism
which is that we're adding a node at a
time.
And it's linking to the nodes that are
already there, who link to the nodes that
are already there and so everything ends
up being connected.
If you remember, we also looked at a
growth model where new nodes were being
added, but the new edges were not
necessarily coming from the new node.
And in that case, of course, you don't
necessarily get everyone in the same
component.
So, for some graphs, it might make sense.
So for example, for web pages, you might
assume that may be the links are only
added when the web created, and then not
added after the fact.
But for other networks, it might make more
sense, you know, if you have social
network, may be initially a person who's
come to a new city doesn't know anyone but
they get to know someone and may get more
people.
So, it really depends, right?
For citation network, this seems to be a
very appropriate model.
And the, the final observation which is
also consistent with the random growth
model is that, again, you have the older
nodes having more edges.
And the newer nodes, the, the young ones,
actually don't really have a chance to
catch up.
Because they're born much later, and so
they're born with you know, when they're
born, they have very few edges.
The older nodes have been around longer
and some of them have gotten really big,
so they're going to continue to
accumulate.
So, if we look at these two nodes, this
one was born at time equals 5, and this
was born at time equals 95.
And so, you can see that they're both kind
of tracking in terms of their growth.
And since this is a log scale, really at
the point that the older node has over
100.
Edges this younger node just has a few
dozen, right?
And it's not, it's not really catching up.
So, you'll have the opportunity to try
this yourself.
So let me see if I can switch to the
model, not this one.
This one, not this one.
Okay, please be this one.
Okay, great.
So sorry about that.
So here in this model you can use
preferential attachments, so let me do
that.
So hopefully, you observed lots of hubs
here.
Now, if we have the probability of
preferential attachment, B serum, and you
can use anything in between as well.
So, we're going to set this up.
And so it might seem similar at first, but
the thing to do is to look at the degree
distribution, and also look at the size of
the nodes to see if you can spot the
difference in the two networks.
Again, they're both growing but one has
preferential attachment and the other one
does not.
So, just to test your understanding
relative to the random growth model, the
degree distribution in the preferential
attachment model is going to resemble a
power-law distribution less or more?
So, just to summarize the, the growth
models the reason for doing growth model
is that most networks aren't born they're
made.
They, they grow over time and this means
that some nodes, the older nodes might
accumulate more than others.
But, if you have this additional
ingredient of preferential attachment,
then nodes that for whatever reason end up
with more edges as the network grows are
going to accumulate even more for edges at
the expense of other less fortunate nodes.
Now, for the assignment this week, what
you'll be doing is looking at the
implications of these models for
diffusion.
And so, even if you're mostly just
listening to the lectures, I think that,
you know, doing this assignment will be,
you know, it will be a cinch and it'll be
interactive in the sense that you'll be
playing with these net logo apps.
So, I encourage you to do it even if you,
you know, even if don't turn in the
assignment, I think it will be worthwhile.
So the, the one part of it will be looking
at, let's see if this is the case.
Oh, nope.
We'll be looking at the Erdos-Renyi random
graph, and here you'll be looking at what
does it mean to have a giant component
that doesn't occupy the whole network for
how are diseases going to spread.
So, you're going to have one node
infected, and then that one node is going
to start infecting others.
And then, those, those nodes will be
affecting others in turn, and you'll see
what happens.
And in another part, you'll be looking at
how quickly information or disease or
other things can spread on the network,
depending on whether the network grows
randomly or grow with preferential
attachment.
So hopefully, it's this one.
Okay, great.
So, you'll be setting up your network and
here it's non non-preferential attachment.
And then, you're going to start spreading
and you're going to see how long it takes
for the information or disease or whatever
to spread.
So, I hope that'll be fun and that, this
is the end of Week 2.
Thanks.