Now, we're ready to talk about the first
few network metrics.
But before we do, I wanted to just
emphasize a few things about
visualizations.
Edward Tufte, who wrote a series of books
on effective data visualization, said, the
success of our visualization is based on
deep knowledge and care about the
substance and the quality, relevance, and
integrity of the content.
In other words, you should know your
network.
You should know what you're visualizing in
order to visualize it most effectively.
Here, his five principles in the Theory of
Graphic Display.
Above all else show the data.
Maximize the data-ink ratio, within
reason.
Erase non-data ink, within reason.
Erase redundant data-ink.
And revise and edit.
Now, this is a little bit different when
we're talking about network
visualizations.
They are actually notoriously hard to
interpret.
And so, we don't really have the luxury of
very clear plots where we're deciding that
we don't want this shading or that.
But what we can take from this is that we
don't necessarily want, no, to be the
spinning visualizations.
Because all that's going to happen is
we're going to see some balls with sticks
sticking out of them that are flying
around in space and no one is going to get
anything out of that.
We should try and see what it is where,
what is interesting in the data?
Perhaps it's the geographical location of
the nodes, perhaps, it's different
communities.
Can you bring out the communities with the
visualization?
Or, maybe there's some especially
significant nodes, because of their
position in the network.
Can you highlight those nodes in some way?
So that is basically what we are going to
be after.
Also, there are things that you want the
automated network layer algorithms to do.
The first I mentioned when we were talking
about the girl's dining table partners
network.
Which was that you want to minimize edge
crossing.
So here is the same network visualized in
two different ways, and this is better,
because it's minimizing edge crossing.
Here, you have an edge crossing, and so,
it looks a little bit less clear that this
node actually doesn't have anything to do
directly with these, that it's actually
closer to this particular node, the one
that it's linked to.
Another thing that you'd like to have are
uniform edge lengths.
And here, you just, like, the nodes that
are connected to be about the same
distance from each other.
And this is better, for example, than this
visualization where we may not know that
this node is connected to these others.
And here, we may not even really see the
edge between these two.
Now, there is an exception, which is when,
excuse me, when you have weighted
networks.
And that happens, for example here, you
may want this node to be far away, because
actually, these edge weights, which we'll
talk about in just a sec, are fairly low.
So you want to represent that distance
between the nodes, and perhaps, these two
that are directly connected are, you know,
a very closely spaced.
Maybe they're very tight, maybe that bond
is very strong, and so, you want them to
be closer together.
So it depends.
Again, you want the network to effectively
represent the data.
Finally, one thing that I was doing is I
was moving nodes away from edges that
weren't incident on them.
So here, for example, we might be confused
thinking that this one node might be
connected, have an edge to this node and,
and another edge to this other node, but
in fact, it doesn't have an edge to either
of them.
It was simply overlapping with that edge.
So, that is something that we'd like to
avoid as well and your ability to avoid
such problems, of course, depends on the
size and the density of the network.
The smaller and the sparser the network,
the more successfully layered algorithms
can satisfy these conditions
simultaneously for all nodes and edges.
Now, let's get to the metrics that we were
going to discuss.
We have the degree and the degree
distribution and then connected
components.
The degree is just going to tell us how
many edges are incident on a node.
So for example, we were talking about the
girl, Eva, and how many other girls had
named her or she had named.
Now, already, you see that there is this
property, directionality of the edge.
And if an edge is directed, we can also
call it an arc or a link.
So, for example, the relationship might be
A likes B, A gave a gift to B, A is B's
child.
There, you can also have undirected edges.
For example A and B like each other, of
course, these relationships aren't always
symmetric.
As we saw in the dining-table partners
network, and actually, in many social
networks.
But, sometimes, the feelings are mutual
and so it can be treated as undirected.
You can have A and B, who are siblings or
A and B who have co-authored papers, for
example.
There are other kinds of edge attributes,
aside from the direction.
So one of them is weight.
For example, if you have the number of
messages sent between two individuals,
that could be the weight of that edge.
And, it makes sense, the more massages
that two individuals send, the higher the
weight you put on that edge.
And of course, you can state, scale it
differently, it could be linear or a log
weight.
And depending on what your goal is, you're
going to chose different and appropriate
weights.
You may also have ranking just as we saw,
that first and second choice of dining
partner, but also may be your rating your
friend from closest to least, least close.
You may also have different types of
edges, so some of your social ties,
friends, some are co-workers, some are
family.
And finally, there may be properties that
you're assigning to the edge that really
depend on the rest of the network and this
we'll get into later.
But some edges might be between kind of
acting as a bridge between two different
areas of the network, and so, they might
have a special role or what's called, the
property's called between betweenness.
So we'll be calculating such properties.
And edges, of course, can have any sort of
property that you calculate on the graph.
Going back to our schoolgirls and their
choices we see both that the edges are
directed and that they have this ranking,
the first and second choice.
Of course, there may be a multitude of
other things that you could add on there,
for example, maybe some of the girls share
a dorm room, etcetera.
But in this data we're just looking at,
first and second choices, and the
direction.
The edge weights that you add can also be
positive and negative weight, for example,
a person trusting or distrusting another.
Here, I'm showing a fraction of the
Epinions graph.
Now, this is a publicly available data set
that we will be actually working with.
And what it is, is Epinions is a website
where users go and they rate products.
Now, product ratings are, they depend on
the individual who's giving the rating.
And not everyone's opinion might be your
own, so you have the option of saying
whether you trust or distrust that
particular individual.
And, this then, influences whose ratings
you're going to be shown and which
products you are recommended.
Now, in this fragment, you can see that
there's negative [laugh] community here of
lots of people distrusting one another
that's tied to your community that
primarily trusts.
And there are very interesting research
questions around this.
For example, what, if you look at sets of
three people, is it true that an enemy of
an enemy is my friend or not?
How does this play out in the, in the
data?
How is this data represented internally?
For example, if you're writing code, or if
you're just using some software, how is
the software representing the network?
The most basic way is with an adjacency
matrix, but we'll also talk about edgelist
and adjacency lists.
Here is a very simple network of five
nodes and here is its adjacency matrix
representation.
And, for example, if we look at node 1,
node 1 is represented by this row and
actually has no outgoing edges.
However, it does have one incoming edge
here from node five.
So let's see how this works.
The entry of the matrix is 1 if node i has
a directed edge to node j and it's 0
otherwise, if i and j don't share an edge.
Usually the diagonal of the matrix, right
here, is 0, because usually, you don't
have self-loops.
However, in some cases, you can have
self-loops.
For example, if the network represents who
nominated whom for a certain office.
Well, individuals can nominate themselves
and you may very well want to have
subloops represented.
And in general, you don't necessarily have
that Aij, that entry is equal to Aji.
This would happen if the network is
undirected.
Well, it would happen, it would be true in
all cases if the network is undirected,
that is i linking to j always means that j
links to i.
Of course, in a directed network, you can
have lots of instances of the edge being
reciprocated.
For example, when you look at friendship
networks, a lot of friendships will tend
to be reciprocated.
We don't have to always use the full
adjacency matrix.
We can also use the edge list and it's
just a bit shorter.
So, you can have, instead of a bunch of
zeros, you just list the, the things that
are there.
So 2 has an edge to 3, 2 has an edge to 4,
etcetera.
Now, you can become even more compact than
that, especially, you may want to do this
if the network is very large and very
sparse.
Sparse means that out of all the possible
people, I could be friends with in this
world, the billions of people, maybe I'm
only friends with a few hundred.
And so, instead of having a billion zeros
I may want to just have an entry that says
Lotto and then it lists, you know, first
friend, second friend, third friend, etc.
It's much more compact.
So, going back to our network of five
nodes, we have an empty adjacency list for
one.
For two, we have that it's has edges to
three and four, etcetera.
Now, after we have done all of this nice
representing we can start to calculate
degree.
And degree just counts the number of
incident edges on a node and we may be
interested in such things as, who is the
most popular?
Can we count how many edges each node has
and which one has the most edges?
So, again, it might matter whether your
network is directed or not.
Imagine that you have a network of who has
loaned money to whom.
If, if it's a loan network, then the
indegree might represent how many
different people did you loan money from?
Outdegree on the other hand might
represent did you lend money to?
And so, in that case, you know owing a lot
of money, having high indegree may be less
desirable than having high outdegree,
having people owe you.
In other networks, you may not care about
the directionality.
So, for example, if it's a friendship
network and people are simply saying who
their friends are, you may just want to
treat the network as undirected and just
count the degree.
Or if you have a network of co-authors,
again, you might just look at how many
co-authors has a particular researcher had
all over the span of the last decade, for
example.
Now, you may be thinking, well, you know,
it's not all about how many friends you
are, you have, or how popular you are.
There could be more important things,
namely having to do with who your friends
are, maybe having a few quality friends,
or having a few well-connected friends
might be more useful in some sense than
having lots and lots of friends who are
otherwise hermits, they don't interact
with anyone else.
So, in week 3, we will consider other
measures of centrality, but for now, we're
just going to treat centrality, this
importance of nodes, simply based on the
immediate network neighborhood.
So your direct neighbors in the network as
opposed to the whole network.
We can calculate these values from the
adjacency matrix.
For outdegree, we're just summing the
nonzero entries in a given row.
So here, the third row tells us that node
number 3 has two outgoing edges, so its
outdegree is two.
On the other hand, from the column by
summing the nonzero entries, we find that
3 has one incoming edge and that is from
node number 2, so its indegree is two.
Now, once we've calculated the degree of
each node, whether it's indegree,
outdegree, or undirected degree, we can
start to construct the degree sequence and
that is actually just the array that
contains the degrees of each node.
The degree sequence in turn can be folded
into a degree distribution, where, for
example for this network, we can count one
node that has zero indegree.
We have four nodes that have indegree one
and three nodes that have indegree two.
And so then this is the Distribution of
degrees in the network, that is, it's
fairly evenly distributed between the
nodes.
The next question we can ask is whether
everything is connected, so here is a
visualization of my Facebook network.
And as you can see, there's several
disconnected components.
This can be quite significant.
For example, if there is some vital
information in one part of the network.
If none of those individuals are talking
to the rest of my network.
Of course, they're linked through me, but
let's, for, imagine that I'm out of the
picture.
So it's just, all my friends are on their
own.
They have to communicate that there would
be no way for that information to spread
from that isolated component to the rest
of the network.
It may not be information, it could be a
virus that's spreading some sort of
disease.
In which case, you may verily, very well
want to be in one of these small
components, because it means that whatever
is spreading in here, you're actually safe
from it, because you don't have any
contact with anyone in the rest of the
network.
And so the overall connectivity of the
network is actually fairly crucial.
We want to know, is everyone reachable
from everyone else for the most part or is
the network so sparse that most people
have no way of contacting each other
through intermediaries?
Again, we're going to pay attention to
whether there, the edges are directed or
not.
And if you do pay attention to that, you
can calculate the strongly connected
components.
The strongly connected components are ones
such that you can reach any node from any
other node in the network by following
directed ties.
So, for example, here with B, C, D and E
you can start with anyone of them and
actually kind of move around here.
Right, so you can, you can reach anyone
from any other one.
However, A is in a component of by itself,
because, even though you can reach A, say
you start at C, you can go to D, you can
go to E, you can go to A.
But once you're at A, you can't go back.
And the condition for the strongly
connected component is that you can really
go from any node to any other node within
the strongly connected component.
And here is another component that's
completely disconnected.
Here, G and H, are in the same strongly
connected component, but again, even
though from F, you can reach G and H, you
can't get back to F.
So F is it's own one node strongly
connected component, while G and H are
anther strongly connected component.
When you have an undirected network or
choose to treat your directed network as
undirected, then you can calculate the
weakly connected components.
And here now, because we're allowing this
edge from E to A to be undirected, that
means you can go from E to A, but you can
also go from A to E.
And now, A, B, C, D, E are all in the same
structure.
Strongly connected component.
And similarly F, H, and G are in the same,
sorry, weakly connected component.
Right?
So this is a weakly connected component.
And this is a weakly connected component.
And if you're dealing with an undirected
network, you can simply just say connect
the component.
You don't always have to say weakly
connected component.
But if it's directed, you want to make the
distinction.
There is also the notion of a giant
component, and it is the largest
component.
And if it encompasses a significant
portion of the graph it can be called a
giant component.
Now, this significant portion of the graph
doesn't actually have to be the majority.
Technically, the definition is that as the
network gets infinitely large, the giant
component is still going to occupy a
finite fraction of it.
So that's the technical definition.
And, you know, practically speaking, if
you observe pretty consistently under
different conditions that your network has
largest component that occupies most of
the network, then you can call it giant
component.
And here is the giant component in, in
this particular network.
So just to recap.
What we showed in this mini-lecture is
that networks can be represented as
matrices, or adjacency lists, or edge
lists and we talked about useful network
metrics that we're going to start out
with.
This is the degrees of the individual
nodes and the degree distribution of the
network overall and then we talked about
connected components.
Strongly connected components, and weakly
connected components in, in directed
graphs, where strongly connected
components obey the directionality of the
edge and then the giant component, which
arises in many, many networks and is the
largest component in a graph that is not
too sparse.
And we'll talk about the giant component
more when we talk about random graphs.