Now we're ready to talk about the first
few network metrics.
But before we do, I wanted to just
emphasize a few things about
visualizations.
Edward Tufte, who wrote a series of books
on effective data visualization said the
success of a visualization is based on
deep knowledge and care about the
substance and the quality, relevance, and
integrity of the content.
In other words, you should know your
network.
You should know what you're visualizing in
order to visualize it most effectively.
Hear his 5 principles in the theory of
graphic display.
Above all else show the data, maximize the
data-ink ratio within reason.
Erase non data ink within reason.
Erase redundant data-ink.
And revise and edit.
Now, this is a little bit different when
we're talking about network
visualizations.
They're actually notoriously hard to
interpret, and so we don't really have the
luxury of very clear plots where we're
deciding that we don't want this shading
or that.
But what we can take from this is that we
don't necessarily want You know, the BD
spinning visualizations.
Because all that's going to happen is
we're going to see some balls with sticks
sticking out of them that are flying
around in space.
And no one is going to get anything out of
that.
We should try and see what it is we're.
What is interesting in the data?
Perhaps it's the geographical location of
the nodes, perhaps it's the different
communities.
Can you bring out the communities with the
visualization?
Or maybe there are some especially
significant nodes because of their
position in the network.
Can you highlight those nodes in some way?
So that is basically what we are going to
be after.
Also there are things that you want the
automated network layer algorithms, to do.
The first I mentioned when we were talking
about the girls' dining table partner's,
network, which was that you want to
minimize edge crossings.
So here is the same network, visualized in
two different ways, and this is better
because it's minimizing edge crossings.
Here you have an edge crossing and so it
looks, a little bit less clear that this
node actually doesn't have anything to do
directly with these, that it's actually
closer to this particular node's the one
that explains too.
Another thing that you'd like to have are
uniform edge lengths.
And here you're just like the nodes that
are connected to be about the same
distance from each other.
And this is better for example than this
visualization where we may not know that
this node is connected to these others,
and here we may not even really see the
edge between these two.
Now there is an exception, which is when,
excuse me, when you have weighted
networks.
And that happens for example here.
You may want this node to be far away
because actually.
These edge weights which we'll talk about
in just a sec are fairly low.
So you want to represent that distance
between the nodes, and perhaps these two
that are directly connected, are you know,
a very closely spaced.
Maybe they're very tight.
Maybe that bond is very strong and so do
want them to be Closer together.
So it depends.
Again, you want the network to effectively
represent the data.
Finally, one thing that I was doing was I
was moving nodes away from edges that
weren't incident on them.
So here, for example, we might be
confused, thinking that this one node
might be connected, have an edge to this
node, and another edge to this other node,
but in fact it doesn't have an edge to
either of them.
It was simply overlapping with that edge.
So that is something that we'd like to
avoid as well.
And your ability to avoid such problems,
of course, depends on the size and the
density of the network.
The smaller and the sparser the network,
the more successfully the erid/g
algorithms can satisfy these conditions
simultaneously for all.
...varied some edges.
Now, let's get to the metrics that we were
going to discuss.
We have the degree and the degree
distribution and then connected
components.
The degree is just going to tell us how
many edges are incident on a note.
So for example, we were talking about the
girl Eva and how many other girls had
named her or she had named.
Now, we're ready to see that there is this
property directionality of the edge.
And if an edge is directed, you can also
call it an arc or a link.
So, for example, the relationship might
be, a likes b.
A gave a gift to b.
A is b's child.
There, you can also have undirected edges.
For example, A and B like each other.
Of course, these relationships aren't
always symmetric as we saw in the Diamond
Cables Partner's network and many social
networks, but sometimes the feelings are
mutual and so it can be treated as
undirect.
Directed.
You can have A and B who are siblings or A
and B who have coauthored papers, for
example.
There are other kinds of edge attributes
aside from the direction.
So, one of them is weight.
For example If you have the number of
messages sent between two individuals,
that could be the weight of that edge.
And it makes sense, the more messages that
you individuals send, the higher the
weight you put on that edge.
And, of course, you can state, scale it
differently.
It could be linear or log weight.
And depending on what your goal is, you're
going to choose different ...and
appropriate, weight.
You may also have ranking, just as we saw
the first and second choice of dining
partner but also maybe your, rating your
friend from closest to least, least close.
You may also have different types of
edges, so some of your social ties are
friends, some are coworkers, some are
family.
And finally there may be the properties
that you're assigning to the edge that
really depend on the rest of the network
and this we'll get into later.
But some edges might be between, kind of
acting as a bridge between two different
areas of the network and so they might
have a special role or So what's called
the properties called between this.
So we'll be calculating, such properties,
and edges can of course have any sort of
property that you calculate on the graph.
Going back to our, school girls and their
choices, we see that both the edges are
directed and that they have this ranking,
the first and the second choice.
Of course there may be a multitude of
other things that you could add on there.
For example, maybe some of the girls share
a dorm room, etc.
But in this data we're just looking at
first and second choices and the
direction.
The edge weights that you add can also be
positive and negative weight.
For example, a person trusting or
distrusting another.
Here I'm showing a fraction of the
Epinions graph.
Now this is a publicly available data set
that we will be actually working with, and
what it is, is, Epinions is a website
where users go and they rate products.
Now product ratings are, they depend on
the individual who's giving the rating,
and, not everyone's opinion might be your
own.
So you have the option of saying whether
you.
Trust or distrust a particular individual,
and this then influences whose ratings you
are going to be shown, and which products
you are recommended.
Now in this fragment you can see that
there's a negative, uh,[LAUGH] community
of lots of people distrusting one another
that's tied to a community that primarily
trusts.
And they're very interesting research
questions around this.
For example, what, if you look at sets of
3 people, is it true that an enemy of an
enemy is my friend or not?
How does this play out in the, in the
data?
How is this data represented entirely.
For example, if you're writing code or if
your just using some software, how is the
software representing the network?
The most basic way is with an adjacency
matrix, but we'll also talk about edgelist
and adjacency list.
Here is a very simple network of five
nodes.
And here is its adjacency matrix
representation.
And for example, if we look at node one,
node one is represented by this row and
actually has no outgoing edges.
However it does have one incoming edge
here from node 5.
So let's see how this works.
The entry in the matrix is 1 if node i has
a directed edge to node j, and it's 0
otherwise, if i and j don't share an edge.
Usually the diagonal of the matrix right
here is zero because usually you don't
have self loops.
However in some cases you can have self
loops.
For example if the network represents who
nominated whom.
For a certain office.
Well, individuals can nominate themselves
and you may very well want to have self
loops represented.
And in general you don't necessarily have
that Aij, that entry, is equal to Aji.
This would happen if the network is
undirected.
Well, it would happen, it would be true in
all cases if Network is undirected that is
i linking to j always means that j links
to i.
Of course, in a directed network, you can
have lots of instances of the edge being
reciprocated.
For example, when you look at friendship
network, a lot of friendship will tend to
be reciprocated.
We don't have to always use the full
adjacency matrix, we can also use the edge
list.
And it's just a bit shorter.
So, you can have, instead of a bunch of
0s, you just list the, the things that are
there.
So, 2 has an edge to 3, 2 has an edge to
4.
Etcetera.
Now you can become even more compact than
that.
Especially you may want to do this if the
network is very large and very sparse.
Sparse means that out of all the possible
people I could be friends with in this
world, the billions of people, maybe I'm
only friends with a few hundred.
And so instead of having a billion zeroes,
I may want to just have an entry that says
lot of.
And then it lists, you know, first friend,
second friend, third friend, etc.
It's much more compact.
So going back to our network of five
nodes, we have an empty adjacency list for
one.
For 2 we have that it's has edges to 3 and
4, et cetera.
Now after we have done all of this nice
representing we can start to calculate
degree.
And degree just counts the number of
incident edges on a node, and we may be
interested in such things as.
Who is the most popular?
Can we count how many edges each node has
and which one has the most edges?
So, again, it might matter whether your
network is directed or not.
Imagine that you have a network of who has
loaned money to, To whom.
If, if it's a lone network, then the
in-degree might represent how many
different people did you loan money from.
Out-degree on the other hand might
represent how many people did you lend
money to.
And so in that case, you know, owing a lot
of money, having high in-degree may be
less desirable than having high
out-degree, having people owe you.
In other networks, you may not care about
the directionality.
So for example if it's a friendship
network, if people are simply saying who
their friends are, you may just want to
treat the network as undirected and just
count The degree, or if you have a network
of coauthors, again, you might just look
at how many coauthors has a particular
researcher had all over the span of the
last decade, for example.
Well, you might be thinking, well, you
know, it's not all about how many friends
you are, you have, or how popular you are.
There could be more important things.
Mainly having to do with who your friends
are.
Maybe having a few quality friends, or
having a few well connected friends might
be more useful, in some sense, than having
lots and lots of friends who are otherwise
hermits.
They don't interact with anyone else.
So, in week 3, we will consider other
measures of centrality.
But for now, we're just going to treat
centrality.
This importance of nodes simply based on
the immediate network neighborhood, so
your direct neighbors in the network as
opposed to the whole network.
We can calculate these values from the
adjacency matrix.
For outdegree, we're just summing the
non-zero entries in a given row, so here
the third row tells us that node number 3
has 2 outgoing edges so its out degree is
2.
On the other hand from the column by
summing the non zero entries we find that
3 has.
One incoming edge and that is from node
number 2, so it's in-degree is 2.
Now once we've calculated the degree of
each node, whether it's in-degree,
out-degree, or undirected degree, we can
start to construct the degree sequence.
And that is actually just the array that
contains The degrees of each node.
The degree sequence in turn can be folded
into a degree distribution.
Where, for example, for this network, we
can count one node that has zero in
degree.
We have four nodes that have in degree
one.
And three nodes that have in degree two.
And so then, this is the distribution of
degrees in the network.
That is, it's fairly evenly distributed
between the nodes.
The next question we can ask is whether
everything's connected.
So here is a visualization of my Facebook
network, and as you can see, there are
several disconnected components.
This can be quite significant.
For example if there is some vital
information in one part of the network, if
none of those individuals are talking to
the rest of my network.
Of course they're linked through me, but
let's first imagine that I'm out of the
picture, so it's just all my friends are
on their own.
They have to communicate that there would
be no way for that information to spread
from that isolated component to the rest
of the network.
It might not be information.
It could be a virus that's spreading some
sort of disease, in which case you may
very well want to be in one of these small
components, because it means that
whatever's spreading in here, you're
actually safe from it.
Because you don't have any contact with
anyone in the rest of the network.
And so the overall connectivity of the
network is actually fairly crucial.
We want to know, is everyone reachable.
From everyone else for the most part or is
the network so sparse that most people
have no way of contacting each other
through intermediaries.
Again we are going to pay attention to
whether their, the edges are directed or
not and if you do pay attention to that
you can calculate the strongly connected
components.
The strongly connected components are ones
such that you can reach any node from any
other node in the network.
By following directed ties.
So, for example, here.
With b, c, d, and e.
You can start with any 1 of them.
And actually kind of move around here.
Right?
So you can, you can reach any one from any
other one.
However, a isn't a component off by
itself.
Because even though you can reach A, say
you start at C, you can go to D, you can
go to E, you can go to A.
But once you're at A, you can't go back.
And the condition for the strongly
connected component is that you can really
go from any node to any other node within
the strongly connected.
Component.
And here's another component that's
completely disconnected.
Here G and H are in the same strongly
connected component but again, even though
from F you can reach G and H, you can't
get back to F.
So F is its own one node strongly
connected component while G and H are
another strongly connected.
Component/g.
When you have an undirected network or you
choose to treat your directed network as
undirected, then you can calculate the
weakly connected components.
And here now, because we're allowing this
edge from E to A to be undirected, that
means you can go from E to A, but you can
also go from A to E, and now A, B, C, D, E
are all in the same structure.
Strongly connected component.
And similarly F, H and G are in the same,
sorry weakly connected component.
So this is a weakly connected component,
and this is a weakly connected component.
And if you're dealing with an under
directed network you can simply just say
connected component, you don't always have
to say weakly connected component.
But if it's directed you want to make the
distinction.
There is also the notion of a giant
component and it is the largest component
and if it encompassed, encompasses the
signification fraction of the graph it can
be called the giant component.
Now this significant portion of the graph
doesn't actually have to be the maturity,
technically the definition is that.
As the network gets infinitely large, the
giant component is still going to occupy a
finite fraction of it.
So that's the technical definition.
And you know practically speaking, if you
observe pretty consistently under
different conditions that your network has
a largest component that occupies most of
the network, then And you can call it the
giant component.
And here's the giant component in, in this
particular network.
So, just to recap, what we showed in this
many lectures that networks can be
represented as matrices or adjacency lists
or edge lists, and we talked about useful
network metrics that we're going to start
out with.
This is the degrees of the individual
nodes, and the degree distribution of the
network overall.
And then we talked about connected
components, strongly connected components
and weakly connected components and,
directed graphs where obey the
directionality of the edge, and then the
giant component which arises in many, many
networks, and is the largest component in
a graph that is not too sparse.
And we'll talk about the giant component
more when we talk about random graphs.