Welcome to week eight our last week.
There is.
One remaining topic that we will talk
about, and in a separate video I'll tell,
tell you about all the interesting things
that we didn't get to cover, but I'll give
you pointers for ways in which you can
pursue them.
So this one thing that we haven't yet
talked about that I do want to talk about
is network resilience.
And this is.
Basically, the question of, what, you
know, so far, we've been nice to our
networks.
We've observed them and seen the
fascinating properties, but in the real
world, networks can be vulnerable, and
it's actually rather important to
understand how resilient they are to two
different kinds of losses.
They can lose nodes this is node
percolation or they could lose edges, so
nodes losing the ability to communicate
with one another.
This is edge percolation.
If you want to understand how two of
those, those two things affect how the
network can function.
Then we're going to look at particular
topologies.
Namely scale-free networks.
And see how random failure of nodes
differs from targeted attack.
That is, random failure might just occur
naturally but targeted attack, if you have
an adversary, they are choosing which
nodes they want to take out.
So how does the network do in one scenario
versus the other?
And how does this depend on its original
topology.
And finally, we'll talk about resilience
in real world networks, and one in
particular, and that is the US power grid.
Let's go back to the question of whether
we're removing nodes or edges.
This has a mapping to lattice percolation,
and.
You can either have here.
Edge percolation, that is, the, here the
nodes are these intersections, and you're
just asking whether the nodes are
connected by these edges.
And it, and what you're looking for is, at
what point does d- a giant component
emerge?
Iii.
But you also may be asking what is the
path length?
Because, if you remember, right path the
peculation threshold these paths can be
rather long.
And if we're thinking about what makes a
network function?
It is that every one is reachable from any
one, any other node.
This has implications for information
flow.
But we also saw, for example this mount
experiment.
That long paths have not that high of a
probability of getting the information
through.
So,
Also having short path lengths between
nodes is important, so we want to,
basically, check both.
The other type of percolation is node
percolation and here we've kind of
switched our presentations a bit because
each of these squares is a node, and it's
simply connected to the four closest
neighbors.
And now each of those squares is either
occupied or not.
And we're going to see what effect that
has on the connected clusters.
So first, edge percolation we're going to
you know, remove each edge with
probability one minus P, meaning that each
edge is there, actually, with probability
P.
And this is just corresponding to the
random failure of links.
And, if we want to target the attack,
we're going to ask, which links should we
remove such that, We have to do the fewest
removals and inflict the most damage in
terms of how much the trying component
shrinks and what the average shortest path
is within the component, and if you think
about what.
What strategies you might want to use.
Well, we've basically already done this
when we used the betweenness algorithm for
community finding.
Remember, the rational there was that, if
we remove pi between these edges.
There, the removal of these edges is most
likely to break up the network into
communities because a lot of shortest
paths went through them.
So removing precisely those edges is going
to most rapidly going to break up the
network.
And.
In a way this, percolation is actually the
reverse of the, or actually these attacks
are the reverse of the process that we
already looked at, which was adding edges.
Right?
We started out with, a fixed number of
nodes and then we added the edges one by
one.
And we just saw at one point, you know we
got these small components and then at
some point we got this large string giant
component and then the network densified
from there on.
And when we looked at the size of the
giant component, it looked something like
this, where you just don't.
Have a giant component.
And then, right around average degree of
one for each node, you, you get the
emergence of the giant component.
So now we're just doing the reverse, which
is where, we're starting out with the
network at some stage, at some density.
And then we're removing the edges and
we're seeing the effect at what point does
the network break up?
So just to check our understanding,
If you had this network here, where each
node has an average degree of 4.6
approximately.
And you, removed a fourth of the edges.
And here I've, highlighted a fourth.
By how much would you reduce the size of
the giant component?
If we look at this, we can see that,
actually, the giant component wasn't even
really affected.
And that is because, if we remove a
quarter of the edges.
We drop from an average degree of four.
Something to an average degree of three,
which is still well above the percolation
threshold.
And we still have most of the network
intact.
Now, let's switch over to removing nodes,
instead of removing edges.
If you remember, we did, I think in the
assignments, or perhaps in the lecture,
this percolation in a regular lattice.
And what [laugh] and this reminds you of,
of water percolating through soil, which
is how the problem was originally
formulated.
And that is, if there are enough gaps,
enough unoccupied sites and these are
actually going to be our nodes.
In the soil, and they merge together,
water can actually seep through.
And, at some point, we're going to get to
this, critical threshold at which point
the water can seep through.
And after that, of course, more and more
water can seep through.
But basically the, at some, proportion of
nodes present, the network starts to
percolate.
Now let's do the same thing in networks as
opposed to lattice.
Here, I'm showing you the Nutella peer to
peer file sharing network, which you have
already encountered in your small worlds
homework.
And, so this is, you know, over a decade
old.
But one characteristic of this network is
that there were a lot of nodes with low
bandwidth even some with dial up modems.
And some nodes who had high bandwidth.
And so you get this hub and spoke kind of
structure.
And naturally.
You know, a lot of high-degree nodes who
are also connected to each other.
So, what happens?
If we remove a random fraction of those
nodes.
Well.
The network actually barely notices.
So here we've removed twenty%, a fifth of
the nodes at random and it looks basically
the same.
If we look at the size of the giant
component, the only thing it's really lost
are those nodes that we removed.
So what happened?
You know, if you look at this network,
you'll realize that there are lots and
lots of nodes with degree one.
And, since this is just random attack,
meaning that nodes are selected at random,
very likely you're going to hit the one
degree nodes and not the few hubs.
And so, removing the, the,
They're called leaf nodes, nodes of degree
one cuz they're just kind of dangling off
the network, doesn't really affect the
network that much.
On the other hand, if you go ahead and
target nodes of your choosing.
So here, we've targeted the high degree
nodes.
You would get similar and even better
results if you targeted the high between
these nodes.
But here, just for simplicity we're doing
high degree.
Well, you know, removing just the 22 most
connected nodes, so that's about three% of
the nodes and the giant component drops in
size almost by a half.
So, why is removing high degree nodes more
effective?
Is it because it removes more nodes?
Because it removes more edges?
Or because it targets the periphery, that
is the outskirts of the network.
Hopefully, what you realized is that if
you remove high-degree nodes, you actually
remove a whole bunch of edges as well.
And so, you, you have much higher impact
by removing those hobs.
And here is the diagram from a paper by
Reka Albert, Hawoong Jeong, and, Laszlo
Barabasi, where they studied, exponential
networks.
So this could be the Eddis-Remi random
graph.
Or it could be a network that is grown
randomly, but without preferential
attachment.
And it doesn't matter if you attack, You
know, with purpose, or if it's just random
failure.
But what you see is that you start out
with a giant component.
And then at some point it's, it's broken
up significantly and eventually you have,
you know, mostly very small components.
Right?
Once you're below the, the peculation
threshold.
On the other hand, the scale free network
is only going to.
Behave like this if there's targeted
attack, that is, you really need to get
those hobs in order to get it to break up
like this.
Otherwise, with random failure, all that
happens is that you keep hitting those
low-degree nodes just by chance.
And, the giant component is going to
shrink modestly and eventually, you know,
shrink even more.
But you'll likely have it throughout this
sort of random failure process.
So.
Besides just looking at the size of the
giant component what we also mentioned
matters is how many hubs it is from one
node to any other.
What we see for the scale free network is
that if you have random failure there's
almost no effect on the average shortest
path which is good.
However the story is quite different for
purposeful attack.
This is where you're taking up.
Taking out the hubs, the average shortest
path actually starts to grow
significantly, even while you're removing
a relatively small fraction of the nodes.
On the other hand, if we look at the
exponential network, the under-finding
random graph, then both failure and attack
have, you know, almost no effect, you
know, just a very, slight effect on the
average shortest path.
If we look at two empirical networks, we
see this confirmed.
So both the physical internet and the
worldwide web are unaffected by random
failure, those are the blue squares here.
And their average shortest path rises
quite dramatically, once you start
targeting the hubs specifically.