So far we have treated the degree
distribution of the network as the most
important factor in how resilient the
network is going to be.
But we've paid no attention to how those
nodes are actually wired together.
And, one simple way of capturing who is
wired to whom is to who is to look at
assortativity.
Specifically degree of assortativity.
In general, assortativity could just mean,
whether like nodes associate with like.
When we're talking about degree
assortativity, we're looking at whether
nodes who are social have lots of
connections, are connected to other nodes
who are likewise social, or is it the
reverse?
Is it that the hobs are associated with
the hermits? The people who have very few
connections?
And, if we look at.
Different kinds of networks.
Here's an example of an assortative
network where you have the hobs connecting
to the other hobs, and the low-degree
nodes connecting to other low-degree
nodes.
Here perhaps this topology is random, it
reminds you of when we grew a preferential
attachment network.
And here, the network is disassortative,
so the hobs like the low-degree nodes and
Yeah, that's the, basically captures it.
There are different ways in which you can
capture this and one is to actually
enumerate all possible pairings of degrees
across the edges.
And look at the same property in a
randomized network to see, and the reason
why it randomizes is just to see.
You know, sometimes at random, you'll have
a high degree node connecting to a low
degree node.
So if you were to do this for the
internet, here's what you would see.
You would see that these medium hubs, and
you know, there, having 30 connections is
not that medium.
Tend to be connected with relatively low
degree nodes.
And the low degree nodes actually end up
being connected with even the, the highest
hubs versus the highest hubs tend to be
connected either with low degree nodes or
with other, you know, very high degree
hubs.
So it gives you a more rich representation
of who is connecting to whom.
You can simplify this, right?
This is a two a 2D histogram, in, in
essence.
Almost a 3D plot, right?
The, the coloring was the third dimension.
We can reduce this to a 2D plot if we look
at the degree of the node.
And then look at the average degree of the
neighbors.
And in fact it, it gives you extra
sensitivity.
Do you remember how I said, you can test
your models by doing additional
measurements?
Well, here is an additional measurement
that, in fact, the regular Barabasi Albert
preferential attachment model, it fails.
It has no trend in the average degree of
the neighbor as a function of the degree
of the node.
In fact, if we look at the physical
Internet. it says that the average degree
of the neighbor falls the higher the
degree of the node and so.
It wasn't until the fitness model which
you know hm, can be just a year later,
within a year where the probability that a
node get one of those new edges associated
with a new node .
It depends, not just on the degree of the
node, but also on its inherent fitness
that you get this kind of relationship
with, which is much closer to what you
observe in real life.
And, there's a, I don't know if you can
hear the crow but it wants to chime in on
this presentation as well.
And then, to simplify even more, you can
just look at a single number, which is
over all the edges.
You just take the correlation between the
degrees of the nodes on either side.
So, for example, for the Internet, you get
this slight disassortativity of minus two.
And of course, you do lose some
information.
For example, yes, you know, on average,
the network is disassortative, but we also
saw that for the highest degree nodes, you
know there was,
They were actually likely to both be
connected to each other and to the very
low degree nodes and it was the middle
that was the, the missing chunk.
Still, it's nice to just be able to
characterize this property with a single
number.
So if you'd like a simple, single number,
then you can just look at this
correlation.
I mentioned that you can talk about
assortative mixing more generally, so if
you were talking about social ties, you
may be looking at race and income and
gender and age.
You can look at food webs herbivores and,
and carnivores I mean I, I'm assuming in
the, in the food web it might be a bit
disassortative there.
And we already discussed the, the.
Internet in terms of the degree but maybe
really what is the property that they're
really connecting on is the type of node
that they are, whether they're high level
connectivity providers, internet service
providers, or consumers.
And in general, when you're talking about
social networks, you you're talking about
homophily the term birds of a feather
flock together is saying exactly this that
individuals in some scenarios will tend to
associate on observable characteristics
for example age and gender.
To check our understanding, will a network
with positive or negative degrees
sortativity be more resilient to attack?
And for this, let's go to Netlogo, and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to set
up a topology, and this network is going
to be disassorted, that is, the
high-degree nodes are going to be
connected to the low-degree nodes.
And the way that I did this was by taking
the originally grown network, and then
rewiring it.
And, the rewiring is accepted if it, in
this case, decreases assortativity, and
not accepted otherwise.
So, let's, let's try and attack this.
And the way that we're going to attack it
is we're going to select the ten highest
degree nodes.
And we observe what happens to the
network.
Now let's grow an assortative network.
And you should see the high degree nodes
clumping together.
And the low degree nodes being pushed out
to the periphery.
And hopefully it will finish rewiring soon
but that's not, well you see this dense
central core.
Now we're going to attack and we can
observe what happens.
And, and here the, the red nodes are in
the giant component.
So going back to our presentation.
Hopefully what you saw was that in the
case of assortative mixing there was very
little impact.
You know, we disconnected these parts of
the network, but in general there was so
much redundancy in that central core that
we didn't end up breaking up the network.
This is sort of the case however, the, a
lot of these nodes are connected to, just
to the hubs and so once the hubs were
removed, the, The network was pretty much
broken up with the removal of just ten