Hi.
Welcome to week four of social network
analysis.
This week, we'll be looking at community
structure within the network.
First, we'll explain why community
structure is interesting.
Mostly it has to do with, instead of one
big hairball you have different regions
within the network that are interacting
with the,
Within that structure more then they are
with the rest of the network.
So, that's going to give you some
information about what is actually going
on besides, oh, my gosh, everything is
connected.
Next, we're going to look at different
definitions. How exactly do you define
that these set of nodes is a community as
opposed to this other set of nodes maybe
is not?
And finally, we're going to look at, you
know, given a network, how can you detect
the communities within it,
And how can you evaluate how good that
those extracted communities are, according
to some criteria.
So first, why do we do it?
And I'll go through three separate
reasons.
The first is, well, these reasons are kind
of social network specific.
So, the first is, you can di, discover
communities of practice.
If you have communication between
individuals, discovering which groups of
individuals tend to communicate more with
each other can tell you what is the, the
structure of collaboration.
So, in a study at done at HP,
What they did was they took all the e-mail
communication,
Organically found water in the
communities.
And then, they compared it against the
actual reporting structure.
So here, grey is e-mail, and black is the
reporting structure.
And they found that in the vast majority
of cases, the different communities.
The communities just corresponded to the
actual reporting structure.
So, if people were, within the same unit
of the organization, they had similar
tasks, similar goals, and they tended to
collaborate with each other.
Okay, fine. This is a validation, right?
You only looked at e-mail communication
and you applied your community detection
algorithm and what was spat out was
totally reasonable.
You got the actual organization back,
which is informative.
You can imagine doing the same study in an
environment where there is no formal
organizational structure, but you still
want to know how did the individuals
organize together.
And this could tell you.
What was particularly interesting in this
study was that, there were a few
communities that were detected which
tended to cross different organizational
units.
And so, when the authors of the study,
Joshua Tyler, and, and others, went and
interviewed those individuals, what they
found was that they had tasks which, in
fact, bridged different parts of the
organization.
So, for example, printers with new
networking functionality.
Well, you needed the printer hardware
people, and you needed the, the people who
know about networking.
And, so the, the, in a way the community
detection was giving a more accurate
picture of the current collaboration
structure than you know, kind of the
formal organization which may or may not
have caught up later,
For example, by re-doing a re-org.
This next example is a very, very classic
example of the Zachary Karate Club.
This sociologist, Zachary, was studying
the interactions within a university
karate club.
And he said, oh, who do you talk to
regularly, who do you like, blah, blah,
blah.
And he got the social network.
Well, while he was studying that karate
club, there was a little bit of infighting
[LAUGH] with individuals in the club, and
the club split in two.
The question is, given who was talking to
whom and who liked whom, could you have
predicted which way the club was going to
split?
And if you can, this is kind of a test for
whether your community finding algorithm
is, is good or not.
Then, you know, that's, that's useful.
Imagine if you can look at any social
network and you can say, well, if things
get tough, I think this, this subset is
going to go so that, that seems useful.
This next example is taken from the book
it's actually kinda a Pajek manual that
teaches you a lot of social network
analysis as well,
It's called Exploratory Social Network
Analysis with Pajek. And, in this
particular data set, which I've now
remapped with, with Geffy, you have
workers at a sawmill.
That is, they're processing wood.
And they're different kinds.
So, here you have the management,
You have English speaking workers they're,
they're marked with E.
And then, you have different roles, so the
Y's work in the yard the P's are the
planers and the M's are the millers.
And, the, what happens was that the
management wanted to introduce a new plan.
and they thought that everybody would be
on board because it was supposed to be
beneficial all around.
What they found instead was that, there
was a lot of resistance with, from
actually the Hispanic workers.
They called in a sociologist who mapped,
who talked to whom frequently, and after
mapping everything out said, I think you
should talk to Juan.
They, the management talked to Juan,
explained the plan, Juan said, I, I will
talk to my friends.
Next day, practically, everyone was on
board with the plan.
So, the quiz is, why did this happen?
What is it about the structure of this
network that would have told you that
talking to Juan is the correct answer?
The correct thing to do.
In this final example of the usefulness of
community finding in social networks,
we'll look at opinion formations.
So, what I'd like you to do is to actually
go to this link.
And let's see if I can find it as well.
Hopefully, hopefully.
Okay.
So, here, you have two choices.
You can either create a network that has
community structure,
And you can lay it out a little bit more
so it's more clear, or you can turn
community structure off.
So, I'm going to create an Erdos-Renyi
graph instead, and then you can do
something called Update Opinion.
And, what happens is that each node looks
at two of its neighbors, and in this case,
it's changed its opinion it's, it's turned
into a square.
And, what it does is, if a majority of its
neighbors have say the red opinion, it
will switch to red if it isn't red
already.
If it's equal numbers of red versus blue,
it will just flip a coin and it may switch
or it may not.
So, I'd like you to do this repeatedly for
the Erdos-Renyi and the two communities
and see in which case the,
You can have divergent opinions persist in
the network in the long run.
That is, you do a lot of updates of the
opinion and sometimes, though not always,
different parts of the network will
maintain a different opinion.
So, let's try and go back to PowerPoint.
Excellent.
Okay. So, this is your quiz question which
I'd like you to answer.
So, hopefully what you saw was that the,
When you have two separate communities,
Because individuals can have more ties
within the community than outside of the
community,
They can actually, you know,
They're seeing like-minded individuals.
And, they can persist in their opinion
even if, say, the rest of the network is
thinking something else. They, they're
just not evenly mixed enough such that
they would be influenced and the opinion
would propagate throughout the network.
So, in this final example, it's a high
resolution map of science that the
researchers did in a very clever way.
They looked at access patterns in online
repositories of scientific articles, for
example, JSTOR,
Or actually, it's scholarly articles. The
JSTOR has a lot of humanities and social
sciences and natural sciences. It's mostly
on the biology end of things.
And what they did was they looked at, if
you access an article in this area, what
other areas are you likely to be exploring
within the same browsing session.
And, if we look a little bit in greater
detail, you can see things, for example,
plant biology being closely tied to
ecology and biodiversity and environmental
science.
And what's more,
You can then collapse these different
communities into metanodes, and see how
the metanodes are then themselves related
to each other.
So, pretty neat, applications of community
finding. And, in the next segment, we'll
get to the more difficult wor, work,
although still fun, of trying to define
what exactly are these communities. And
then, in the third segment, we'll look at
how do you actually find them.